1. From my grandfather Verus I learned good morals and the government of my temper. From
the reputation and remembrance of my father, modesty and a manly character. From my mother,
piety and beneficence and abstinence, not only from evil deeds, but even from evil
thoughts and, further, simplicity in my way of living, far removed from the habits of
the rich. From my great-grandfather, not to have frequented public schools and to have
had good teachers at home, and to know that on such things a man should. From my governor,
to be neither of the Green nor of the Blue Party at the games in the circus,
nor a partisan either of the Parmularius or the Scutarius at the gladiators' fights.
From him, too, from Diognotus, not to busy myself about trifling things, and not to give
credit to what was said by miracle-workers and jugglers about incantations and the
driving away of daemons in such things, and not to breed quails for fighting, nor to give
myself up passionately to such things, and to endure freedom of speech, and to have become
intimate with philosophy, and to have been a hearer, first of Bacchus, then of Tandisus
and Marcianus, and to have written dialogues in my youth, and to have desired a plank-bed
and ninskin, and whatever else of the kind belongs to the Grecian discipline. You need
to add some text for me to talk. From Rusticus, I received the impression that my character
required improvement and discipline, and from him I learned not to be led astray to
sophisticated emulation, nor to writing on speculative matters, nor to delivering little
hortatory orations, nor to showing myself off as a man who practices much discipline
or does benevolent acts in order to. You need to add some text for me to talk.
Make a display, and to abstain from rhetoric and poetry and fine writing, and not to
walk about in the house in my outdoor dress, nor to do other things of the kind, and
write my letters with simplicity, like the letter which Rusticus wrote from Sinuesa
to my mother, and with respect to those who have offended me by words or done me wrong.
You need to add some text for me to talk. To be easily disposed, to be pacified and
reconciled, as soon as they have shown a readiness to be reconciled, and to read
carefully, and not to be satisfied with a superficial understanding of a book, nor
hastily to give my assent to those who talk over much, and I am indebted to him for
being acquainted with the discourses of Epictetus, which he, you need to add some
text for me to talk, from Apollonius. I learned freedom of will and undeviating
steadiness of purpose, and to look to nothing else, not even for a moment, except to
reason. You need to add some text for me to talk. Yielding, and not peevish
giving his instruction, and to have had before my eyes a man who clearly
considered his experience and his skill in expounding philosophical principles as
the smallest of his merits, and from him I learned how to receive from friends
what are esteemed favors, without being either humbled by them or letting
them pass. You need to add some text for me to talk, from Sextus. A
benevolent disposition, and the example of a family governed in a fatherly
manner, and the idea of living conformably to nature, and gravity
without affectation, and to look carefully after the interests of
friends, and to tolerate ignorant persons and those who form opinions
without consideration, he had the power of readily. You need to add
some text for me to talk, accommodating himself to all, so that
the intercourse with him was more agreeable than any flattery, and at the same
time he was most highly venerated by those who associated with him, and he
had the faculty both of discovering and ordering, in an intelligent and
methodical way, the principles necessary for life, and he never showed
anger or any other, passion, but was entirely free from passion, and
also most affectionate, and he could express approbation without noisy
display, and he possessed much knowledge without ostentation. You need to add
some text for me to talk, from Alexander the Grammarian, to refrain from
fault, finding, and not in a reproachful way, to chide those who
uttered any barbarous or solicistic or strange, sounding expression,
but dexterously, to introduce the very expression which ought to have
been used, itself, not about the word, or by some other fit suggestion,
from fronto, I learn to observe what envy and duplicity and hypocrisy
are in a tyrant, and that generally those among us who are called
patricians are rather deficient in paternal affection. From
Alexander the Potonic, not frequently nor without necessity to say
to anyone, or to write in a letter, that I have no leisure, nor
continually to, excuse the neglect of duties required by our
relation to those with whom we live, by alleging urgent inoccupations,
from Cotulus, not to be indifferent when a friend finds fault, even
if he should find fault without reason, but to try to restore him
to his usual disposition, and to be ready to speak well of teachers,
as it is reported of Domitius and Athenodotus, from my brother
Severus, to love my kin, and to love truth, and to love justice,
and through him I learn to know, Thrasya, Helvidius, Cato, Dion,
Brutus, and from him I received the idea of a polity in which
there is the same law for all, a polity administered with regard
to equal rights and equal freedom of speech, government which
respects most of all the freedom of the governed, I learn from
him also consistency and undeviating steadiness in my regard for
philosophy, and a disposition to do good, with respect to those
whom he condemned, and that his friends had no need to conjecture
what he wished or did not wish, but it was quite plain, from
maximus I learned self-government, and not to be led aside
by anything, and cheerfulness in all circumstances, as well as an
illness, and a just admixture in the moral character of
sweetness and dignity, you need to add some text for me to talk,
I observe that everybody believed that he thought as he spoke,
and that in all that he did he never had any bad intention,
and he never showed amazement and surprise, and was never in
a hurry, and never put off doing a thing, nor was perplexed
nor dejected, nor did he ever laugh to disguise his vexation,
nor, on the other hand, was he ever, he was accustomed to do
knacks of beneficence, and was ready to forgive, and was free
from all falsehood, you need to add some text for me to talk,
in my father I observe mildness of temper, and unchangeable
resolution in the things which he had determined, to every
man according to his deserts, and a knowledge derived from
experience of the occasions for vigorous action, I observe,
too, that no man could ever think that he was despised by
Maximus, or ever venture to think himself a better man, he
had also the art of being humorous in an agreeable way, and
I observe that he had overcome all passion for boys, and he
considered himself no more than any other citizen, and he
released his friends from all obligation, to sup with him,
or to attend him of necessity when he went abroad, and those
who had failed to accompany him by reason of any urgent
circumstances always found him the same, you need to add some
text for me to talk, I observe, too, his habit of careful
inquiry in all matters of deliberation, and his
persistency, and that he never stopped his investigation
to being satisfied with appearances which first present
themselves, and that his disposition was to keep his
friends, and not to be soon tired of them, nor yet to be
extravagant in his affection, you need to add some text
for me to talk, be satisfied on all occasions, and
cheerful, and to foresee things a long way off, and to
provide for the smallest without display, and to check
immediately popular applause in all flattery, and to be
ever watchful over the things which were necessary for
the administration of the empire, and to be a good
manager of the expenditure, you need to add some text
for me to talk, to endure the blame which he got for
such conduct, and he was neither superstitious with
respect to the gods, nor did he court men by gifts, or
by trying to please them, or by flattering the
populace, but he showed sobriety in all things and
firmness, and never any mean thoughts or action, nor
love of novelty, and the things which conduce in any
way to the commodity of life, and of which fortune
gives an abundant supply, he used, without arrogance,
and without excusing himself, so that when he had
them, he enjoyed them without affectation, and when
he had them not, he did not want them. No one
could ever say of him that he was either a sophist
or a homebred flippant slave or a pedant, but
every one acknowledged him to be a man ripe, perfect,
above flattery, able to manage his own and other
men's affairs. Besides this, he honored those who
were true philosophers, and he did not reproach
those who pretended to be philosophers, nor yet
was he easily led by them. He was also easy in
conversation, and he made himself agreeable without
any offensive affectation. He took a reasonable
care of his body's health, not as one who was
greatly attached to life, nor out of regard to
personal appearance, nor yet in a careless way. But
so, that, through his own attention, he very
seldom stood in need of the physician's art, or
of medicine or external applications. You need to
add some text for me to talk. He was most
ready to give way, without envy to those who
possessed any particular faculty, such as that of
eloquence or knowledge of the law, or of
anything else, and he gave them his help, that
each might enjoy reputation according to his
deserts. Further, he was not fond of change, nor
unsteady, but he loved to stay in the same
places, and to employ himself about the same
things. And after his paroxysms of headache,
he came immediately fresh and vigorous to his
usual occupations. You need to add some text
for me to talk. His secrets were not, but very
few and very rare, and these only about public
matters. He did not take the bath at
unseasonable hours. He was not fond of
building houses, nor curious about what he
ate, nor about the texture and color of his
clothes, nor about the beauty of his slaves.
His dress came from Lorium, his villa on the
coast. We know how he behaved to the
people, collector at Tusculum, who asked his
pardon, and such was all his behavior. There
was in him nothing harsh, nor implacable, nor
violent, nor, as one may say, anything
carried to the sweating point. But he
examined all things severally, as if he had
abundance of time and without confusion, in
an orderly way, and that might be applied
to him, which is recorded of Socrates, that
he was able both to abstain from, and to
enjoy, those things which many are too weak
to abstain from, and cannot enjoy without
excess. But to be strong enough both to
bear the one, and to be sober in the
other, is the mark of a man who has a
perfect and invincible soul, such as he
showed in the illness of Maximus. To the
gods, I am indebted for having good
grandfathers, good parents, a good sister,
good teachers, good associates, good
kinsmen and friends, nearly everything
good. Further, I owe it to the gods that
I was not hurried into, any offense
against any of them, though I had a
disposition which, if opportunity had
offered, might have led me to do
something of this kind, but, through
their favor, there never was such a
concurrence of circumstances as put me
to the trial. You need to add some text
for me to talk. Further, I am thankful
to the gods that I was not longer
brought up with my grandfather's
concubine, and that I preserved the
flower of my youth, and that I did
not make proof of my virility before
the proper season, but even end
deferred the time. You need to add
some text for me to talk. Me to the
knowledge that it is possible for a
man to live in a palace, without
wanting either guards or embroidered
dresses or torches and statues and
such, with respect to the things which
must be done for the public interest
in a manner that befits a ruler. You
need to add some text for me to
talk. I thank the gods for giving me
such a brother, who was able by his
moral character to rouse me to
vigilance over myself, and who, at
the same time, pleased me by his
respect and affection, that my
children have not been stupid nor
deformed in body, that I did not make
more proficiency in rhetoric, poetry
and the other studies, in which I
should. You need to add some text for
me to talk. Perhaps have been
completely engaged if I had seen that
I was making progress in them, that
I made haste to place those who
brought me up in the station of
honor, which they seemed to desire
without putting them off, with hope
of my doing it some time after. You
need to add some text for me to
talk. Receive clear and frequent
impressions about living according to
nature, and what kind of a life that
is, so that, so far as depended on
the gods and their gifts and help and
inspirations, nothing hindered me
from forthwith living according to
nature, though I still fall short of
it through my own fault and through
not observing thee. You need to add
some text for me to talk. Admonitions
of the gods, and, she spent the last
years of her life with me, that,
whenever I wished to help any man in
his need, or on any other occasion, I
was never told that I had not the
means of doing it, and that to myself
the same necessity never happened, to
receive anything from another. So
simple, that I had abundance of good
masters for my children, and that
remedies have been shown to me by
dreams, both others, and against
blood-spitting and giddiness, and that,
when I had an inclination to
philosophy, I did not fall into the
hands of any sophist, that I did not
waste my time on, writers of histories,
or in the resolution of syllogisms,
or occupy myself about the
investigation of appearances in the
heavens, for all these things require
the help of the gods and fortune,
among the Quadi at the Granua. Book 2
Begin the morning by saying to thyself,
I shall meet with the busybody, the
ungrateful, arrogant, deceitful,
envious, unsocial. All these things
happen to them by reason of their
ignorance of what is good and evil.
You need to add some text for me to
talk. But I who have seen the nature
of the good, that it is beautiful, and
of the bad, that it is ugly, and the
nature of him who does wrong, that it
is akin to me, not only of the same
blood or seed, but that it participates
in the same intelligence and the same
portion of the divinity. What is ugly,
nor can I be angry with my kinsmen,
nor hate him, for we are made for
cooperation, like feet, like hands,
like eyelids, like the rows of the
upper and lower teeth. To act against
one another, then, is contrary to
nature. And it is acting against one
other to be vexed, and to turn away.
Whatever this is that I am, it is a
little flesh and end breath, and the
ruling part. Throw away thy books, no
longer distract thyself. It is not
allowed. But as if thou wast now
dying, despise the flesh, it is blood
and bones and a network, a
contextual of nerves, veins, and
arteries. See? The breath? Also? What
kind of a thing it is? Air? And not
always the same, but every moment
send out and again sucked in. The third
then is the ruling part. Consider thus,
thou art an old man, no longer let
this be a slave, no longer be pulled
by the strings like a puppet to
unsocial movements, no longer either be
dissatisfied with thy present. All that
is from the gods is full of
providence. That which is from fortune
is not separated from nature, or
without an interweaving and
evolution with the things which are
ordered by providence. From thence all
things flow, and there is besides
necessity, and that which is for the
advantage of the whole universe, of
which thou art apart. But that is good
for every part of nature, which the
nature of the whole brings. Let these
principles be enough for thee, let
them always be fixed opinions. But
cast away the thirst after books,
that thou mayest not die murmuring,
but cheerfully, truly, and from thy
heart thankful to the gods. Remember
how long thou hast been putting off
these things, and how often thou hast
received an opportunity from the gods,
and yet dost not use it. Thou must now
at last perceive of what universe thou
art apart, and of what administrator of
the universe thy existence is an
efflux, and that a limit of time is
fixed for thee, which, if thou dost
not, use for clearing away the
clouds from thy mind, it will go and
thou wilt go, and it will never return.
Never moment think steadily as a Roman,
and a man to do what thou hast in hand
with perfect and simple dignity, and
feeling of affection and freedom, and
thou will give thyself relief if
thou doest every act of thy life.
Thou seest how few the things are,
the which, if a man lays hold of, he
is able to live, a life which flows
in quiet, and is like the existence of
the gods, for the gods on their part
will require nothing more from him who
observes these things. Do wrong to
thyself, do wrong to thyself, my soul,
but thou wilt no longer have the
opportunity of honoring thyself. Every
man's life is sufficient, but thine
is nearly finished, though thy soul
reverence is not itself, but places
thy felicity in the souls of others. Do
the things external which fall upon thee
distract thee, give thyself time to
learn something new and good, and cease
to be whirled around, but then thou must
also avoid being carried about the
other way. For those too are triflers
who have wearied themselves in life
by their activity, and yet have no
object to which to direct every
movement and, in a word, all their
thoughts. Through not observing what
is in the mind of another, a man has
seldom been seen to be unhappy. But
those who do not observe the movements
of their own minds must of. You need to
add some text for me to talk. This
thou must always bear in mind. What is
the nature of the whole, and what is my
nature, and how this is related to
that? The Ephrastus, in his comparison
of bad acts, such a comparison as
one would make in accordance with the
common notions of mankind, says, like
a true philosopher, that the offenses
which are committed through desire
are more blamable than those which are
committed through anger. For he who is
excited by anger seems to turn away
from reason with a certain pain and
unconscious contraction. But he who
offends through desire, being
overpowered by pleasure, seems to be
in a manner more intemperate and
more womanish in his offenses. You
need to add some text for me to
talk. Rightly then, and in a way
worthy of philosophy, he said that
the offense which is committed with
pleasure is more blamable than that
which is committed with pain, and on the
whole the one is more like a person who
has been first wronged and through
pain is compelled to be angry. Since it
is possible that thou mayest apart
from life this very moment, regulate
every act and thought accordingly. But
to go away from among men, if there
are gods, is not a thing to be
afraid of. For the gods will not
involve thee in evil. But if indeed
they do not exist, or if they have no
concern about human affairs, what is it
to me to live? In a universe devoid
of gods, or devoid of providence. But
in truth they do exist, and they do
care for human things, and they have
put all the means in man's power to
enable him not to fall into real
evils. And as to the rest, if there
was anything evil, they would have
provided for this also, that it should
be altogether in a man's power not to
fall into it. You need to add some text
for me to talk. But neither through
ignorance, nor having the end
knowledge, but not the power to guard
against or correct these things, is it
possible that the nature of the
universe has overlooked them? Nor is
it possible that it has made so
great a mistake, either through want
of power or want of skill, that good
and evil should happen
indiscriminately to the you. Now that
which does not make a man worse, how
can it make a man's life worse? But
death, certainly, and life, honor and
dishonor, pain and pleasure, all these
things equally happen to good men
and bad, being things which make us
neither better nor worse. You need to
add some text for me to talk. How
quickly all things disappear, in the
universe the bodies themselves, but in
time the remembrance of them. What is
the nature of all sensible things, and
particularly those which attract with
the bade of pleasure or terrify by
pain, or are noised abroad by
vapoury fame, are? All this it is the
part of the intellectual faculty to
observe. To observe, too, who these
are, whose opinions and voices give
What death is, and the fact that, if a
man looks at it in itself, and by the
abstractive power of reflection resolves
into their parts all the things which
present themselves to the
imagination in it, he will then
consider it to be nothing else than
an operation of nature. If anyone is
afraid of an operation of nature, he is
a child. Therefore, they are neither
This, however, is not only an operation
of nature, but it is also a thing which
conduces to the purposes of nature. To
observe, too, how man comes near to
the deity, and by what part of him,
and when this part of man is so
disposed. You need to add some text
for me to talk. Nothing is more
wretched than a man who traverses
everything and around, and pries into
the things beneath the earth, as the
poet says, and seeks by conjecture what
is in the minds of his neighbors,
without perceiving that it is
sufficient to attend to the daemon
within him, and to reverence it
sincerely for their excellence, and
the things from men should be dear to
us by reason of kinship, and
sometimes even, in a manner, they move
our pity by reason of men's ignorance
of good and bad, being not less than
that which deprives us of the power of
distinguishing things that are white,
and reverence of the daemon consists
in keeping it pure from passion and
thoughtlessness, and dissatisfaction
with what comes from gods and men.
Though thou shouldst be going to live
three thousand years, and as many
times ten thousand years, still
remember that no man loses any other
life than this which he now lives,
nor lives any other than. The longest
and shortest are thus brought to the
same, for the present is the same to
all, though that which perishes is not
the same, and so that which is lost
appears to be a mere moment. For a man
cannot lose either the past or the
future, for what a man has not, how
can anyone take this from him? You
need to add some text for me to
talk. These two things then thou must
bear in mind, the one that all things
for maternity are of like forms and
come round in a circle, and that it
makes no difference whether a man
shall see the same things during a
hundred years or two hundred or an
infinite time. For the present is the
only thing of which a man can be
deprived if it is true that this is
the only thing which he has, and that
a man cannot lose a thing if he has
it not. For what was said by the
Cynicmonimus is manifest, and
manifest, too, is the use of what was
said. The soul of man does violence to
itself, first of all when it becomes
an abscess and, as it were, a tumor on
the universe so far as it can, for to
be vexed at anything which happens is
a separation of ourselves from nature,
in some part of which the natures of
all other things are contained. In the
next place the soul does violence to
itself when it turns away from any
man, or even moves towards him with
the intention of injuring, such as
are the souls of those who are angry.
In the third place the soul does
violence to itself when it is
overpowered by pleasure or by pain.
Fourthly, when it plays a part and does
or says anything insincerely and
untruly. Fifthly, when it allows any
act of its own and any movement to
be without an aim and does anything
thoughtlessly and without considering
what it is, it being right, that even
the smallest things be done with
reference to an end, and the end of
animals is to follow the reason and the
law of the most ancient city in polity.
Of human life the time is a point, and
the substance is in a flux, and the
perception dull, and the composition
of the whole body subject to
putrefaction, and the soul a whirl,
and fortune hard to divine, and fame
a thing devoid of judgment. And, to
say all in a word, everything which
belongs to the body is a stream, and
what belongs to the soul is a dream and
vapor, and life is a warfare and a
stranger sojourn. You need to add some
text for me to talk, but this
consists in keeping the daemon within
a man free from violence and unharmed
superior to pains and pleasures, doing
nothing without purpose, nor yet falsely
and with hypocrisy, not feeling the
need of another man's doing or not
doing anything, besides accepting all
that happens and all that is allotted
as coming from thence, wherever it is,
from whence he himself came, and
finally waiting for death with a
cheerful mind as being nothing else
than a dissolution of the elements of
which every living being is
compounded. What then is that which
is able to conduct a man? One thing
and only one philosophy. And, but if
there is no harm to the elements
themselves, in each continually
changing into another, why should a man
have any apprehension about the change
in dissolution of all the elements? We
ought to consider not only that our
life is daily wasting away and a
smaller part of it is left, but
another thing also must be taken into
the account. That if a man should live
longer, it is quite uncertain whether
the understanding will still continue
sufficient for the comprehension of
things, and retain the power of
contemplation which strives to acquire
the knowledge of the divine and the
human. You need to add some text for me
to talk, for if he shall begin to fall
into dotage. Perspiration and nutrition
and imagination and appetite, and
whatever else there is of the kind,
will not fail. But the power of
making use of ourselves, and filling
up the measure of our duty, and
clearly separating all appearances, and
considering whether a man should now
depart from life, and whatever else of
the kind, absolutely requires a
disciplined reason. All this is
already extinguished, for it is
according to nature, and nothing is
evil which is according to nature.
Look! We ought to observe also that
even the things which follow after
the things which are produced according
to nature, contain something pleasing
and attractive. For instance, when
bread is baked, some parts are split
at the surface, and these parts which
thus open, and have a certain fashion
contrary to the purpose of the baker's
art, are beautiful in a manner, and in
a peculiar way excite a desire for
eating, eyebrows, and the foam which
flows from the mouth of wild boars,
and many other things, though they are
far from being beautiful, if a man
should examine them severly. Still,
because they are consequent upon the
things which are formed by nature, help
to adorn them, and they please the mind,
so, that if a man should have a feeling
and deeper insight with respect to
the things which are produced in the
universe, there is hardly one of those
which follow by way of consequence,
which will not seem to him to be in
a manner disposed so as to give
pleasure. You need to add some text
for me to talk. And so, he will see
even the real gaping jaws of wild
beasts with no less pleasure than
those which painters and sculptors show
by imitation, and in an old woman and
an old man, he will be able to see a
certain maturity and comeliness, and the
attractive loveliness of young
persons he will be able to look on
with chaste eyes, okay, will present
themselves, not pleasing to every
man, but to him only who has become
truly familiar with nature and her
works, and again, figs, when they are
quite ripe, gape open, and, in the ripe
olives, the very circumstance of their
being near to rottenness adds a
peculiar beauty to the fruit. The
Childe foretold the deaths of many,
and then fate caught them too.
Alexander and Pompeius and Chias Caesar,
after so often completely destroying
whole cities and in battle cutting to
pieces, many ten thousands of cavalry
and infantry. Heraclitus, after so
many speculations on the conflagration
of the universe, was filled with water
internally and died smeared all over
with mud, and lice destroyed Democritus,
and other lice killed Socrates. What
means all this? Thou hast embarked,
thou hast made the voyage, thou art
come to shore, wan, get out. If indeed
to another life there is no want of
gods, not even there. But if to a
state without sensation, thou wilt cease
to be held by pains and pleasures, and
to be a slave to the vessel, which is
as much inferior as that which serves
it is. Superior, for the one is
intelligence and deity, the other is
earth and corruption. Do not waste the
remainder of thy life in thoughts
about others, when thou dost not refer
thy thoughts to some object of common
utility. For thou looses the
opportunity of doing something else,
when thou hast such thoughts as
these. What is such a person doing,
and why, and what is he saying, and what
is he thinking of, and what is he
contriving? And whatever else of the
kind makes us wander away from the
observation of our own ruling power.
We ought then to check in the series
of our thoughts everything that is
without a purpose and useless, but most
of all the over-curious feeling and
the malignant, and a man should use
himself to think of those things,
only about which, if one should
With perfect openness thou mightest
immediately answer this or that, so that
from thy words it should be plain
that everything in thee is simple and
benevolent, and such as befits a
social animal, and one that cares not
for thoughts about pleasure, or sensual
enjoyments at all, nor has any rivalry
or envy and suspicion, or anything
else for which. Thou wouldst blush, if
thou shouldst say that thou hadst it in
thy mind. You need to add some text for
me to talk. For the man who is such,
and no longer delays being among the
number of the best, is like a priest
and minister of the gods, using too
the deity which is planted within him,
which makes the man uncontaminated by
pleasure, unharmed by any pain,
untouched by any insult, feeling no
wrong, a fighter in the noblest fight,
by any passion, died deep with justice,
accepting with all his soul everything
which happens, and is assigned to him
as his portion, for it is only what
belongs to himself that he makes
the matter for his activity, and he
constantly thinks of that which is
allotted to himself out of the sum
total of things, and he makes his
own acts fair, and he is persuaded that
his own portion is good, for the lot
which is assigned to each man is
carried along with him, and carries him
along with it, and he remembers also
that every rational animal is his
kinsman. But as to those who live not
so, he always bears in mind what kind
of men they are both at home and from
home, both by night and by day, and
what they are, and with what men they
live, and in pure life. Accordingly, he
does not value at all the praise which
comes from such men, since they are not
even satisfied with themselves. Labor
not unwillingly, nor without regard to
the common interest, nor without due
consideration, nor with distraction,
nor let studied ornaments set off
thy thoughts, and be not either a
man of many words, or busy about too
many things. Be the guardian of a
living being, manly, and of ripe age,
and engaged in matter political, and a
Roman, and a ruler, who has taken his
post like a man waiting for the signal
which summons him from life, and ready
to go, having need neither of oath nor
of any man's testimony. You need to add
some text for me to talk. If thou
findest in human life anything
better than justice, truth, temperance,
fortitude, and, in a word, anything
better than thy own mind's self. This
turn to it with all thy soul, and
enjoy that which thou hast found to be
the best. You need to add some text
for me to talk. But if nothing appears
to be better than the deity which has
planted in thee, which has subjected
to itself all thy appetites, and
carefully examines all the
impressions, and, as Socrates said,
has detached itself from the
persuasions of sense. You need to add
some text for me to talk. Of less
values in this, give place to nothing
else, for thou dost once diverge and
incline to it, thou wilt no longer
without distraction. Pleasure should
come into competition with that which
is rationally and politically or
practically good. Be cheerful also, and
seek not external help nor the
tranquility which others give. But do
thou, I say, simply and freely choose
the better, and hold to it. But that
which is useful is the better. Well then,
if it is useful to thee as a rational
being, keep to it. But if it is only
useful to thee as an animal, say so,
and maintain thy judgment without
arrogance. Only take care that thou
makest the inquiry by a sure method.
You need to add some text for me to
talk. Never value anything as
profitable to thyself, which shall
compel thee to break thy promise, to
lose thy self-respect, to hate any man,
to suspect, to curse, to act the
hypocrite, to desire anything which
needs walls and curtains. For he who
has preferred to everything,
intelligence and daemon and the
worship of its excellence, acts no
tragic part, does not groan, in will
not need either solitude or much
company. And what is chief of all, he
will live without either pursuing or
flying from death. But whether for a
longer or a shorter time he shall have
the soul enclosed in the body, he cares
not at all. For even if he must depart
immediately, he will go as readily as
if he were going to do. Anything else
which can be done with decency and
order, taking care of this only all
through life, that his thoughts turn
not away from anything which belongs
to an intelligent animal and a member
of a civil community. In the mind of
one who is chastened and purified, thou
wilt find no corrupt matter, nor
impurity, nor any sore skinned over.
Besides, there is in him nothing
servile, nor affected, nor too closely
bound to other things, nor yet
detached from other things, nothing
worthy of blame, nothing which seeks a
hiding place. Reverence the faculty
which produces opinion. On this faculty
it entirely depends whether there shall
exist, in thy ruling part, any opinion
inconsistent with nature and the
constitution of the rational animal.
Throwing away, then, all things. Hold
to these only which are few, and
besides, bear in mind that every man,
this barren mind, this present time,
which is an indivisible point, and
that all the rest of his life is
either past or it is uncertain. Short,
then, is the time which every man lives,
and small the nook of the earth where
he lives. To the aids which have been
mentioned, let this one still be added,
make for thyself a definition or
description of the thing which is
presented to thee, so as to see
distinctly what kind of a thing it
is in its substance, in its nudity, in
its complete entirety. You need to add
some text for me to talk, for nothing is
so productive of elevation of mind as
to be able to examine methodically and
truly every object which is presented
to thee in life, and always to look
at things, so as to see at the same
time what kind of universe this is,
and what kind of use everything
performs in it, and what value
everything has with reference to the
whole, and you need to add some text
for me to talk. What with reference to
man, who is a citizen of the highest
city, of which all other cities are like
families, what each thing is, and of
what it is composed, and how long it
is the nature of this thing to endure,
which now makes an impression on me,
and what virtue I have need of with
respect to it, such as gentleness,
manliness, truth, fidelity. You need to
add some text for me to talk.
Wherefore on every occasion a man
should say, This comes from God, and this
is according to the apportionment and
spinning of the thread of destiny, and
such, like coincidence and chance, and
this is from one of the same stock,
and a kinsman and partner, one who
knows not, however, what is according
to his nature. But I know, for this
reason, I behave towards him according
to the natural law of fellowship, with
benevolence and justice. At the same
time, however, in things indifferent I
attempt to ascertain the value of each.
You need to add some text for me to
talk. If thou workest at that which
is before thee, following right reason,
seriously, vigorously, calmly, without
allowing anything else to distract thee,
but keeping thy divine part pure,
according to nature, and with
heroic truth in every word and sound
which thou utterest, thou wilt live
happy, and there is no man who is able
to prevent this. As physicians have
always their instruments and knives
ready for cases which suddenly require
their skill, so do thou have
principles ready for the understanding
of things divine and human, and for
doing everything, even the smallest,
with a recollection of the bond which
unites the divine and human. For
neither wilt thou do anything well
which pertains to man, without at the
same time having a reference to things
divine, nor the contrary, no longer
wander at hazard. For neither wilt thou
read thy own memoirs, nor the acts of
the ancient Romans and Hellenes, and
the selections from books which thou was
reserving for thy old age. Hasten,
then, to the end which thou hast
before thee, and throwing away idle
hopes come to thy own aid if thou
carest at all for thyself, while it
is in thy power. They know not how many
things are signified by the words
stealing, sewing, buying, keeping quiet,
seeing what ought to be done, for this
is not affected by the eyes, but by
another kind. You need to add some
text for me to talk. To receive the
impressions of forms by means of
appearances belongs even to animals. To
be pulled by the strings of desire
belongs both to wild beasts and to
men who have made themselves into
women, and to a Filaris and a Nero, and
to have the intelligence that guides
to the end things which appear
suitable belongs also to those who do
not believe, in the gods, and who
betray their country and do their
impure deeds when they have shut the
doors. If then, everything else is
common to all that I have mentioned.
Obediently as a god, neither saying
anything contrary to the truth, nor
doing anything contrary to justice.
Body, soul, intelligence, to the body,
belong sensations, to the soul,
appetites, to the intelligence
principles. And if all men refuse to
believe that he lives a simple,
modest, and contented life, he is
neither angry with any of them, nor
does he deviate from the way which
leads to the end of life, to which a
man ought to come, pure, tranquil,
ready to depart, and without any
compulsion, perfectly reconciled to
his lot. Book 4. That which rules within,
when it is according to nature, is so
affected with respect to the events
which happen, that it always easily
adapts itself to that which is and is
presented to it. You need to add some
text for me to talk, for it requires
no definite material, but it moves
towards its purpose, under certain
conditions, however, and it makes a
material for itself out of that which
opposes it, as fire lays hold of
what falls into it, by which a small
light would have been extinguished, but
when the fire is strong, it soon
appropriates to itself the matter which
is, heaped on it, and consumes it, and
rises higher by means of this very
material. Let no act be done without
a purpose, nor otherwise, than
according to the perfect principles of
art. Men seek retreats for themselves,
houses in the country, seashores,
and mountains for
to desire such things very much, but
this is altogether a mark of the most
common sort of men, for it is in thy
power, whenever thou shalt choose to
retire into thyself. For nowhere,
either with more quiet or more freedom
from trouble, does a man retire than
into his own soul, particularly when he
has within him such thoughts that by
looking into them he is immediately
imperfect. Tranquility, and I affirm that
tranquility is nothing else than the
good ordering of the mind. Constantly
then give to thyself this retreat, and
renew thyself, and let thy principles
be brief and fundamental, which, as
soon as thou shalt recur to them,
will be sufficient to cleanse the
soul completely, and to send thee back
free from all discontent with the
things to which thou returnest. For
with what art thou discontented, with
the badness of men? Recall to thy mind
this conclusion, that rational animals
exist for one another, and that to
endure is a part of justice, and that
men do wrong involuntarily, and
consider how many already, after
mutual enmity, suspicion, hatred, and
fighting, have been stretched dead,
reduced to ashes, but perhaps? Thou
art dissatisfied with that which is
assigned to thee out of the
Recall to thy recollection this
alternative. Either there is
providence or atoms, fortuitous
concurrence of things, or remember the
arguments by which it has been proved
that the world is a kind of political
community, and be quiet at last. But
perhaps corporeal things will still
fasten upon thee. Consider then
further, that the mind mingles not
with the breath, whether moving
gently or violently. When it has once
drawn itself apart and discovered its
own power, and think also of all that
thou hast heard and assented to about
pain and pleasure, and be quiet at
last. But perhaps the desire of the
thing called fame will torment thee.
See how soon everything is forgotten,
and look at the chaos of infinite
time on each side of the present,
and the emptiness of applause, and
the changeableness, nand want of
judgment. For the whole earth is a
point, and how small a nook in it is
this thy dwelling, and how few are
there in it, and what kind of people
are they who will praise thee. This
then remains. Remember to retire into
this little territory of thy own, and
above all do not distract or strain
thyself, but be free, and look at
things as a man, as a human. But
among the things readiest to thy
hand, to which thou shall turn, let
there be these, which are two. The
other is, that all these things which
thou seest change immediately, and will
no longer be, and constantly bear in
mind how many of these changes thou
hast already witnessed. You need to add
some text for me to talk. If our
intellectual part is common, the
reason also, in respect of which we
are rational beings, is common. If
this is so, common also is the reason
which commands us what to do, and what
not to do. If this is so, for of what
other common political community will
anyone say that the whole human race
are members? You need to add some text
for me to talk, for as my earthly
part is a portion given to me from
certain earth, and that which is
watery from another element, and that
which is hot and fiery from some
peculiar source, for nothing comes out
of that which is nothing, as nothing
also returns to non-existence, so
also the intellectual part comes from
some source. Death, such as generation
is, a mystery of nature, a composition
out of the same elements, and a
decomposition into the same, and
altogether not, a thing of which any
man should be ashamed. For it is not
contrary to the nature of a
reasonable animal, and not contrary
to the reason of our constitution. It is
natural that these things should be
done by such persons. It is a matter of
necessity, and if a man will not have
it so, he will not allow the fig tree
to have juice. But by all means bear
this in mind, that within a very
short time both thou and he will be
dead, and soon not even your names
will be left behind. Take away thy
opinion, and then there is taken away
the complaint, I have been harmed. Take
away the complaint, I have been harmed,
and the harm is taken away. That which
does not make a man worse than he was,
also does not make his life worse, nor
does it harm him, either from without
or from within. The nature of that
which is universally useful has been
compelled to do this. Consider that
everything which happens, happens
justly, and if thou observe us
carefully, thou wilt find it to be
good. I do not say only with respect
to the continuity of the series of
things, but with respect to what is
just, and as if it were done by one
who assigns to, observe then as thou
hast begun, and whatever thou doest,
do it in conjunction with this, the
being good, and in the sense in
which a man is properly understood to
be good. Keep to this in every
action, and do not have such an
opinion of things as he has who does
thee wrong, or such as he wishes thee
to have, but look at them as they are
in truth. A man should always have
these two rules, in readiness. The
one, to do only whatever the reason
of the ruling and legislating faculty
may suggest, for the use of men. The
other, to change thy opinion, if
there is any one at hand who sets
thee right and moves thee from any
opinion. But this change of opinion
must proceed only from a certain
persuasion, as of what is just or of
common advantage, and the like, not
because it appears pleasant or brings
reputation. Why then dost not thou use
it? For if this does its own work,
what else dost thou wish? What else
dost thou wish? Thou shalt disappear
in that which produced thee, but
rather thou shalt be received back
into its seminal principle by
transmutation. Many grains of
frankincense on the same altar, one
falls before, another falls after, but
it makes no difference. Within ten
days thou wilt seem a god to those to
whom thou art now, a beast and an ape,
if thou wilt return to thy principles
and the worship of reason. Do not act
as if thou were going to live ten
thousand years. Death hangs over thee.
While thou livest, while it is in
thy power, be good. How much trouble
he avoids who does not look to see
what his neighbor says, or does, or
thinks, but only to what he does
himself, that it may be just and pure,
or as Agathon says, look not round at
the end appraved, morals of others,
but run straight along the line
without deviating from it. You need to
add some text for me to talk. He
who has a vehement desire for
posthumous fame does not consider
that every one of those who remember
him will himself also die very soon.
But suppose that those who will
remember are even immortal, and that
the remembrance will be immortal. What
then is this to thee? For thou now
rejectest unseasonably the gift of
nature, clinging to something else.
Neither worse then nor better is a
thing made by being praised. I affirm
this also of the things which are
called beautiful, by the vulgar, for
example, material things and works of
art. That which is really beautiful has
no need of anything, not more than law,
not more than truth, not more than
benevolence or modesty. Which of these
things is beautiful because it is
praised, or spoiled by being blamed?
Is such a thing as an emerald made
worse than it was, if it is not
praised? For as here, the mutation of
these bodies, after a certain
continuance, whatever it may be, and
their dissolution make room for other
dead bodies. So the souls which are
removed into the air after subsisting
for some time are transmuted and
diffused. Nand assume a fiery nature by
being received into the seminal
intelligence of the universe. And in,
this way, make room for the fresh
souls which come to dwell there. If
souls continue to exist, how does the
air contain them from eternity? But how
does the earth contain the bodies of
those who have been buried from time
so remote? But we must not only think
of the number of bodies which are thus
buried, but also of the number of
animals which are daily eaten by us and
the other animals. For what a number is
consumed, and thus in a manner buried
in the bodies of those who feed on
them. And nevertheless, this earth
receives them by reason of the
changes of these bodies into blood,
and the transformations into the
or the fiery element, the division into
that which is material and that which
is the cause of form, the formal. Do
not be worried about, but in every
movement have respect to justice,
and on the occasion of every
impression maintain the faculty of
comprehension or understanding.
Everything harmonizes with me, which
is harmonious to thee, O universe.
Nothing for me is too early nor too
late, which is in due time for thee.
Everything is fruit to me which thy
seasons bring, O nature. From thee are
all things, in thee are all things, to
thee all things return. The poet says,
Dear city of set crops, and wilt not
thou say, Dear city of Zeus, occupy
thyself with few things, says the
philosopher, if thou wouldst be
tranquil. But consider, if it would
not be better to say, Do what is
necessary, and whatever the reason of
the animal which is naturally social
requires, and as it requires. For this
brings not only the tranquility, which
comes from doing well, but also that
which comes from doing few things.
Accordingly, on every occasion a man
should ask himself, Is this one of
the unnecessary things? Try how the
life of the good man suits thee, the
life of him who is satisfied with
his portion out of the whole, and
satisfied with his own, just acts and
benevolent disposition. Look also at
these. Do not disturb thyself. Make
thyself all simplicity. In a word, thy
life is short. Thou must turn to
profit the present by the aid of
reason and justice. But can a certain
order subsist in thee, and disorder
in thee all, and this too when all
things are so separated and
diffused and sympathetic? A black
character, a womanish character, a
stubborn character, bestial, childish,
animal, stupid, counterfeit,
scurrilous, fraudulent, tyrannical.
If he is a stranger to the universe,
who does not know what is in it, no
less is he a stranger who does not
know what is going on in it. He is
a runaway, who flies from social
reason. He is blind, who shuts the
eyes of the understanding. He is poor,
who has need of another, and has not
from himself all things which are
useful for life. He is an abscess on
the universe, who withdraws and
separates himself from the reason
enough our common nature, through
being displeased with the things
which happen. For the same nature
produces this, and has produced thee
too. He is a piece rent asunder
from the state, who tears his own
soul from that of reasonable animals,
which is one. The one is a
philosopher, without a tunic, and
the other, without a book. Here is
another half-naked, bred, I have not,
he says. And I abide by reason, and I
do not get the means of living out
of my learning, and I abide by my
reason. Love the art, poor as it may
be, which thou hast learned, and be
content with it, and pass through
the rest of life like one who has
entrusted to the gods with his
whole soul all that he has, making
thyself neither the tyrant nor the
slave of any man. Consider, for
example, the times of Vespasian. Thou
wilt see all these things, people
marrying, bringing up children, sick,
dying, warring, feasting, trafficking,
cultivating the ground, flattering,
obstinately arrogant, suspecting,
plotting, wishing for some to die,
grumbling about the present, loving,
heaping of treasure, desiring
counselship. Well then, that life of
these people no longer exists at all,
again, removed to the times of Trajan.
Again, all is the same, their life too
is gone. In like manner view also the
other epochs of time and of whole
nations, and see how many after great
efforts soon fell and were resolved
into the elements. But chiefly, thou
shouldst think of those whom thou hast
thyself known, distracting themselves
about idle things, neglecting to do
what was in accordance with their proper
constitution, and to hold firmly to
this, and to be content with it. For
thus, thou wilt not be dissatisfied,
if thou apply'st thyself to smaller
matters no further than is fit. And
the words which were formerly familiar
are now antiquated, so also the names
of those who were famed of old are now
in a manner antiquated, Camillus,
Cezo, Volasus, Leonidas, and a
little after also Scipio and Cato,
then Augustus, then. And herein it is
necessary to remember that the
attention given to everything has its
proper value and proportion. For all
things soon pass away and become a
mere tale, and complete oblivion soon
buries them. And I say this of those
who have shown in a wondrous way,
for the rest, as soon as they have
breathed out their breath, they are
gone, and no man speaks of them. And
to conclude the matter, what is even
an eternal remembrance, a mere nothing?
What, then, is that about which we
ought to employ our serious pains?
Willingly give thyself up to Clotho,
one of the fates, allowing her to
spin thy thread into whatever thing
she pleases. Everything is only for a
day, both that which remembers and
that which is remembered. Observe
constantly that all things take place
by change, and accustom thyself to
consider that the nature of the
universe loves nothing so much as to
change the things which are and to
make new things like them. For
everything that exists is in a manner,
the seed of that which will be. But
thou art thinking only of seeds
which are cast into the earth, or
into a womb. But this is a very
vulgar notion. Thou wilt soon die,
and thou art not yet simple, not free
from perturbations, nor without
suspicion of being hurt by external
things, nor kindly disposed. Towards
all, nor dost thou yet place wisdom
only in enacting justly. Examine men's
ruling principles, even those of the
wise, what kind of things they avoid,
and what kind they pursue. What is
evil to thee does not subsist in
the ruling principle of another, nor
yet in any turning and mutation of thy
corporeal covering. Where is it then? It
is in that part of thee in which
subsists the power of forming opinions
about evils. Let this power then not
form such opinions, and all as well.
And if that which is nearest to it,
the poor body, is burnt, filled with
matter and rottenness. Nevertheless,
let the part which forms opinions
about these things be quiet. That is,
let it judge that nothing is either
good, which can happen equally to the
bad man and the good. You need to add
some text for me to talk.
Constantly regard the universe as
one living being, having one substance
and one soul, and observe how all
things have reference to one
perception, the perception of this one
living being, and how all things act
with one movement, and how all things
are the cooperating causes of all
things which exist. Observe, too, the
continuous spinning of thee. For that
which happens equally, to him who
lives contrary to nature, and to him
who lives according to nature, is
neither according to nature, nor
contrary to nature.
Soul-bearing about a corpse, as
Epictetus used to say. It is no
evil for things to undergo change,
and no good for things to subsist
in consequence of change. Time is like
a river made up of the events which
happen, and a violent stream, for as
soon as a thing has been seen, it is
carried away, and another comes in its
place. Everything which happens is as
familiar, and well known, as the
rose in spring. For such is disease,
death, and death, and calumny,
treachery, or whatever else delights
fools or vexes them. In this series
of things, those which follow are
always aptly fitted to those which
have gone before. For this series is
not like a mere enumeration of
disjointed things, which has only a
necessary sequence, but it is a
rational connection. No mere
succession, but a certain wonderful
relationship. You need to add some
text for me to talk, and think too
of him who forgets wither the way
leads, and that men quarrel with
that with which they are most
constantly in communion. The reason
which governs the universe, and the
things which daily meet with, seem to
them strange, and consider that we
ought not to act and speak as if we
were asleep. For even in sleep we
seem to act and speak, and that we
ought not, like children who learn
from their parents, simply to act and
speak as we have been taught. Always
remember the saying of Heraclitus,
that the death of earth is to become
water, and the death of water is to
become air, and the death of air is to
become fire. And reversely, if any God
told thee that thou shalt die
to-morrow, or certainly on the day
after to-morrow, thou wouldst not
care much whether it was on the
third day, or on the morrow. Unless
thou wast in the highest degree
mean-spirited, for how small is the
difference. Think continually how many
physicians are dead, after often
contracting their eyebrows over the
sick. Power over men's lives with
terrible insolence, as if they were
immortal, and how many cities are
entirely dead, so to speak, Helis,
and Pompeii, and Herculaneum, and
others innumerable. So think it no
great thing to die after as many
years as thou canst name, rather
than to-morrow. To conclude, always
observe how ephemeral and worthless
human things are, and what was
yesterday a little mucus to. Morrow
will be a mummy, or ashes. Pass then
through this little space of time
conformably to nature, and end thy
journey in content, just as an olive
falls off when it is ripe. Blessing
nature who produced it. Be like the
promontory against which the waves
continually break, but it stands
firm and tames the fury of the
water around it. Unhappy am I, because
this has happened to me. Not so, but
happy am I, though this has happened
to me, because I continue free from
pain, neither crushed by the present,
nor fearing the future. For such a
thing as this might have happened to
every man. But every man would not
have continued free from pain on such
an occasion. Why, then, is that
rather a misfortune than this, a good
fortune? And does a thing seem to thee
to be a deviation from man's nature,
when it is not contrary to the will of
man's nature? Well, thou knowest the
will of nature. Will then this which
has happened prevent thee from being
just, magnanimous, and temperate,
prudent, secure against inconsiderate
opinions and falsehood? Will it
prevent thee from having modesty,
freedom, and everything else, by the
presence of which man's nature
obtains all that is its own? Remember
too, on every occasion, which leads
thee to vexation, to apply this
principle, not that this is a
misfortune, but that to bear it
nobly is good fortune. What more,
then, have they gained than those who
have died early? Altogether the
interval is small between birth and
death, and consider with how much
trouble, and in company with what sort
of people, and in what a feeble body
this interval is laboriously passed.
Do not then consider life a thing of
any value, for look to the immensity of
time behind thee, and to the time which
is before thee, another boundless
space. Always run to the short way,
and the short way is the natural.
Accordingly say and do everything in
conformity with thee. For such a
purpose frees a man from trouble and
warfare in all artifice and
ostentatious display.
And art thou unwilling to do the work
of a human being, and dost thou not
make haste to do that which is
according to thy nature? It is
necessary, however. Nature has fixed
bounds to this too. She has fixed
bounds both to eating and drinking.
Yet in thy acts it is not so, but
thou stopest short of what thou
canst do. So thou lovest not
thyself, for if thou didst, thou
wouldst love thy nature and her
will. But those who love their
several arts exhaust themselves in
working at them, unwashed and
without food, but thou valuest thy
own nature. Less than the
turner values the turning art, or
the dancer, the dancing art, or the
lover of money values his money, or
the. And such men, when they have a
violent affection to a thing, choose
neither to eat nor to sleep, rather
than to perfect the things which they
care for. How easy it is to repel
and to wipe away every impression
which is troublesome or unsuitable.
And judge every word and deed which
are according to nature to be fit
for thee, and be not diverted by the
blame which follows, from any people
nor by their words. But if a thing
is good to be done or said, do not
consider it unworthy of thee. For
those persons have their peculiar
leading principle, and follow their
movement, which things do not thou
regard, but go straight on following
thy own nature. And the common
nature in the way of both is one. I
go through the things which happen
according to nature, until I shall
fall and rest, breathing out my
breath into that element out of
which I daily drawed in, and
falling upon that earth out of which
my father collected the seed and my
mother, the blood and my nurse the
milk. Drink, which bears me when I
tread on it and abuse it for so
many purposes, thou sayest, men
cannot admire the sharpness of thy
wit. Be it so, but there are many
other things of which thou canst
not say, I am not formed for them
by nature. Show those qualities,
then, which are altogether in thy
power, sincerity, gravity, endurance
of labour, aversion to pleasure,
contentment with thy portion, and
with few things, benevolence,
frankness, no love of superfluity,
freedom from trifling magnanimity.
Dost thou not see how many
qualities thou art immediately able
to exhibit, in which there is no
excuse of natural incapacity and
unfitness, and yet thou still
remainest voluntarily below the
mark? Or art thou compelled through
being defectively furnished by
nature to murmur, and to be stingy,
and to flatter, and to find fault
with thy poor body, and to try to
please men, and to make great
display, and to be so restless in
thy mind? No, by the gods, but
thou mightest have been delivered
from these things long ago, only
if in truth thou canst be charged
with being rather slow and dull of
comprehension. Thou must exert
thyself about this also, not
neglecting it, nor yet taking
pleasure in thy dullness. One man,
when he has done a service to
another, is ready to set it down
to his account as a favor
conferred. Another is not ready to do
this, but still in his own mind he
thinks of the man as his debtor,
and he knows what he has done. A
third in a manner does not even know
what he has done, but he is like a
vine which has produced grapes, and
seeks for nothing more after it has
once produced its proper fruit. As a
vine, a man who has done a good
service to another, does not call
out for others to come and see.
But he goes on to another act, as a
vine goes on to produce again the
grapes in season. Must a man then be
one of these, who in a manner act
thus without observing it? Yes. But
this very thing is necessary, the
observation of what a man is doing.
For, it may be said, if a man
It is characteristic of the social
animal to perceive that he is
working in a social manner, and
indeed, to wish that his social
partner also should perceive it.
It is true what thou sayest,
but thou dost not rightly
understand what is now said.
But if thou wilt choose to
understand the meaning of what is
said, do not fear that for this
reason thou wilt omit any social
act. A prayer of the Athenians
Rain, rain, O dear Zeus, down on
the plowed fields of the Athenians
and on the plains. In truth, we
ought not to pray at all, or we
ought to pray in this simple and
noble fashion. Just as we must
understand, when it is said, that
Aesculapius prescribed to this man
horse exercise, or bathing in cold
water, or going without shoes.
So, we must understand it. When it
said, for in the first case
prescribed means something like
this. He prescribed this for this
man as a thing adapted to
procure health, and in the
second case it means that which
happens to, or suits, every man
is fixed in a manner for him
suitably to his destiny.
And four, this is what we mean
when we say that things are
suitable to us. As the
Romans say of squared stones in
walls, or the pyramids, that they
are suitable, when they fit them
to one another in some kind of
connection. For there is all
together, one fitness, harmony.
And as the universe is made up
out of all bodies to be such a
body as it is, so out of all
existing causes, necessity,
destiny, is made up to be such a
cause as it is. And even those
who are completely ignorant
understand what I mean, for they
it, necessity, destiny, brought
this to such a person. Many as a
matter of course, even among his
prescriptions, are disagreeable,
but we accept them in the hope
of health. And so accept
everything which happens, even
if it seemed disagreeable,
because it leads to this, to
the health of the universe, and
to the prosperity and felicity
of Zeus the universe. For he
would not have brought on any
man what he has brought, if it
were not useful for the whole.
You need to add some text for me
to talk. For two reasons, then
it is right to be content with
that which happens to thee. The
one, because it was done for
thee, and prescribed for thee,
and in a manner had reference
to thee, originally from the
most ancient causes spun with
thy destiny, of and the
other, because even that which
comes severly to every man is
to the power which administers
the universe, a cause of
felicity and perfection, nay
even of its very continuance,
neither does the nature of
anything, whatever it may be,
cause anything which is not
suitable to that which is
directed by it. For the
integrity of the whole is
mutilated, if thou cuttest
off anything whatever, from
the conjunction and the
continuity, either of the
parts or of the causes.
You need to add some text for
me to talk. Be not disgusted
nor discouraged, nor
dissatisfied, if thou dost not
succeed in doing everything
according to right principles.
But when thou hast failed,
return back again, master,
but act like those who have
sore eyes and apply a bit of
sponge and egg, or as another
applies a plaster, or
drenching with water. And
thou dost cut off, as far
as it is in thy power, when
thou art dissatisfied, yanned
in a manner triest, to put
anything out of the way. For
thus thou wilt not fail to
obey reason, and thou wilt
repose in it. And remember
that philosophy requires only
the things which thy nature
requires, but thou wouldst
have something else which
is not according to nature.
For what is more agreeable
than wisdom itself, when
thou thinkest of the
security and the happy
course of all things which
depend on the faculty of
understanding and knowledge?
Things are in such a kind of
envelopment that they have
seemed to philosophers, not a
few, nor those common
philosophers, altogether
unintelligible, nay even to
the Stoics. But is not this
the very reason why pleasure
deceives us? And consider
if magnanimity, freedom,
simplicity, equanimity,
piety are not more agreeable,
and all our assent is
changeable. For where is the
man who never changes?
Carry thy thoughts, then to
the objects themselves, and
consider how short-lived they
are, and worthless, and that
they may be in the
possession of a filthy wretch,
or a whore, or a robber.
Then turn to the morals of
those who live with thee,
and it is hardly possible
to endure even the most
agreeable of them, to say
nothing of a man being
hardly able. In such
darkness, then, and dirt,
and in so constant a and
flux, both of substance and
of time, and of motion,
and of things moved, what
there is worth being highly
prized, or even an object
of serious pursuit, I cannot
imagine, that nothing
will happen to me, which
is not conformable to the
nature of the universe, and
the other, that it is in my
power never to act contrary
to my God and Daemon,
about what am I now employing
my own soul. On every
occasion I must ask myself
this question, and inquire,
what have I now in this
part of me, which they call
the ruling principle, and
whose soul have I now, that
of a child, or of a young
man, or of a feeble woman,
or of a tyrant, or of a
domestic animal, or of a
wild beast? What kind of
things those are which
appear good to the many,
we may learn even from
this. For if any man should
conceive certain things as
being really good, such as
prudence, temperance,
justice, fortitude, he
would not, after having
first conceived these,
endure to listen to
anything which should not
be in harmony with what
is really good. But, if
a man has first conceived
as good the things which
appear to the many to
be good, he will listen,
and readily receive, as
very applicable, that which
was said by the comic
writer. Thus, even the
many perceive the
difference, for were it
not so, this saying
would not offend, and
would not be rejected in
the first case, while we
receive it when it is
said of wealth, and of
the means which further
luxury and fame, as said
fitly and wittily. Go on,
then, and ask if we
should value and think
those things to be good,
to which, after their
first conception in the
mind, the words of the
comic writer might be
aptly applied, that he who
has them, through pure
abundance, has not a
place to ease nymph-self
in. I am composed of the
formal and the material,
and neither of them will
perish into nonexistence,
as neither of them came
into existence out of
nonexistence. Every part
of me, then, will be
reduced by change into
some part of the
universe, and that
again will change into
another part of the
universe, and so on
forever. And by
consequence of such a
change, I, too, exist,
and those who begot me,
and so on forever in the
other direction. For
nothing hinders us from
saying so, even if the
universe is administered
according to definite
periods of revolution.
Reason and the reasoning
art, philosophy, are
powers which are
sufficient for
themselves and for
their own works. They
move, then, from a
first principle which is
their own, and they make
their way to the end
which is proposed to
them. And this is the
reason why such acts
are named katorthasais,
or right acts, which
word signifies that
they proceed. None of
these things ought to be
called a man's, which
do not belong to a man,
as man. Neither, then,
does the end of man
lie in these things,
nor yet that which
aids to the
accomplishment of this
end, and that which
aids towards this end,
is that which is good.
Besides, if any of these
things did belong to
man, it would not be
right for a man to
despise them and to
set himself against
them, nor would a man
be worthy of praise,
who showed that he did
not want these things,
nor would he who stinted
himself in any of them
be good, if indeed
these things were good.
But now the more of
these things a man
deprives himself of,
or of other things
like them, or even
when he is deprived
of any of them, the
more patiently he endures
the loss. Just in the
same degree he is a
better man. And, such as,
are thy habitual
thoughts. Such also
will be the character
of thy mind. For the
soul is died by the
thoughts. But he must
live in a palace. Well,
then, he can also
live well in a palace.
And again, consider
that for whatever
purpose each thing
has been constituted,
for this it has been
constituted, and towards
this it is carried,
and its end is.
Now the good for the
reasonable animal is
society. For that we
are made for society
has been shown above.
Is it not plain that
the inferior exist
for the sake of the
superior? But the
things which have life
are superior to those
which have not life,
and of those which
have life, the
superior are those
which have reason.
To seek what is
impossible is madness,
and it is impossible
that the badge should
not do something of
this kind. Nothing
happens to any man
which he is not formed
by nature to bear. The
same things happen to
another, and either
because he does not see
that they have happened,
or because he would
show a great spirit he
is firm and remains
unharmed. It is a
shame, then, that
ignorance and conceit
should be stronger
than wisdom. Things
themselves touch. Not
the soul, not in the
least degree, nor have
they admission to the
soul, nor can they
turn or move the
soul. But the soul
turns and moves itself
alone, and whatever
judgments it may think
proper to make, such
it makes for itself
the things. In one
respect, man is the
nearest thing to me,
so far as I must do
good to men and endure
them. You need to add
some text for me to
talk. Now it is true
that these may impede
my action, but they
are no impediments to
my affects and
disposition, which have
the power of acting
conditionally and
changing. For the
mind converts and
changes every hindrance
to its activity into
an aid, and so that
which is a hindrance is
made a furtherance to
an act. Reverence that
which is best in the
universe, and this is
that which makes use
of all things and
directs all things. And
in like manner also
reverence that which
is best in thyself,
and this is of the
same kind as that,
for in thyself also,
that which makes use
of everything else is
this, and thy life is
directed by this. But
if the state is harmed,
thou must not be angry
with him who does
harm to the state. For
substance is like a
river in a continual
flow, and the
activities of things
are in constant change,
and the causes work
in infinite varieties,
and there is hardly
anything which stands
still. How then is
he not a fool who is
puffed up with such
things, or plagued
about them and makes
himself miserable? For
they vex him only for
time, and a short time.
I entink, of the
universal substance,
of which thou hast
a very small portion,
and of universal time,
of which a short and
indivisible interval
has been assigned to
thee, and of that
which is fixed by
destiny, and how small
a part of it thou art.
Does another do me
wrong? Let him look
to it. He has his
own disposition,
his own activity. I now
have what the
universal nature wills
me to have, and I do
what my nature now
wills me to do.
Let the part of thy
soul which leads
and governs be
undisturbed by the
movements in the flesh,
whether of pleasure
or of pain, and let
it not unite with them,
but let it circumscribe
itself and limit
those affects to their
parts. But when these
affects rise up to
the mind, by virtue
of that other sympathy,
that naturally exists
in a body which is
all one, then thou
must not strive to
resist the sensation,
for it is natural.
But let not the
ruling part of itself
add to the sensation
the opinion that it
is either good or bad.
Live with the gods.
And he does live
with the gods, who
constantly shows to them.
His own soul is
satisfied with that
which is assigned to him,
and that it does
all that the
daemon wishes, which
Zeus hath given to
every man for his
guardian and guide.
A portion of himself.
And this is every man's
understanding and reason.
Art thou angry with
him whose armpits stink?
him whose mouth
smells foul?
What good will
this anger do thee?
He has such a mouth.
He has such armpits.
It is necessary that
such an emanation
must come from such things.
But the man has reason,
it will be said.
And he is able,
if I wish thee well
of thy discovery.
Well then,
and thou hast reason,
by thy rational faculty,
stir up his rational faculty,
show him his error,
admonish him,
for if he listens,
thou wilt cure him,
and there is no need of anger,
as thou intendest to live
when thou art gone out.
So it is in thy
power to live here.
But if men do not permit thee,
then get away out of life,
yet so as if
thou wert suffering no harm.
Why dost thou think
that this is any trouble?
But so long as nothing of the kind
drives me out,
I remain, am free,
and no man shall hinder me
from doing what I choose.
And I choose to do
what is according to the nature
of the rational and social animal.
The intelligence of the universe
is social.
Accordingly,
it has made the inferior things
for the sake of the superior,
and it has fitted
the superior to one another.
Thou seest how it has
subordinated,
coordinated,
and assigned to everything
its proper portion,
and has brought together
into concord with one another
the things which are the best.
How hast thou behaved hitherto
to the gods, thy parents,
brethren, children, teachers,
to those who looked after thy infancy,
to thy friends, kinsfolk,
to thy slaves?
You need to add some text
for me to talk,
and call to recollection
both how many things
thou hast passed through,
and how many things
thou hast been able to endure,
and that the history of thy life
is now complete,
and thy service is ended,
and how many beautiful things
thou hast seen,
and how many pleasures
and pains thou hast despised,
spurned,
and to how many ill-minded folks
thou hast shown a kind disposition.
Why do unskilled
and ignorant souls disturb him
who has skill and knowledge?
Soul then has skill and knowledge.
Soon, very soon,
thou wilt be ashes or a skeleton,
and either a name or not even a name,
but name is sound and echo,
and the things which are much valued in life
are empty and rotten and trifling,
and like little dogs biting one another,
and little children quarreling,
laughing, and then straightway weeping.
But fidelity and modesty
and justice and truth
are fled up to Olympus
from the widespread earth.
If the objects of sense are easily changed
and never stand still,
and the organs of perception are dull
and easily receive false impressions,
and the poor soul itself
is an exhalation from blood,
but to have good repute
amidst such a world as this
is an empty thing,
why then dost thou not wait
in tranquility for thy end,
whether it is extinction
or removal to another state?
Why, what else than to venerate
gods and bless them,
and to do good to men,
and to practice tolerance
and self-restraint?
But as to everything
which is beyond the limits
of the poor flesh and breath,
to remember that this is neither thine
nor in thy power.
Thou canst pass thy life
in an equable flow of happiness,
if thou canst go by the right way
and think and act in the right way.
These two things are common,
both to the soul of God
and to the soul of man,
and to the soul of every rational being,
not to be hindered by another,
and to hold good to consist
in the disposition to justice,
practice of it,
and in this to let thy desire
find its termination.
If this is neither my own badness
nor an effect of my own badness,
and the common wheel is not injured,
on why am I troubled about it?
Do not be carried along inconsiderately
by the appearance of things,
but give help to all
according to thy ability
and their fitness,
and if they should have sustained loss.
In matters which are indifferent,
do not imagine this to be a damage,
for it is a bad habit.
But as the old man, when he went away,
asked back his foster child's top,
remembering that it was a top,
so do thou, in this case also.
Yes, but they are objects
of great concern to these people.
Wilt thou too then be made a fool
for these things?
I was once a fortunate man,
but I lost it,
I know not how.
But fortunate means that a man
has assigned to himself a good fortune,
and a good fortune
is good disposition of the soul,
good emotions, good actions.
Book 6
The substance of the universe
is obedient and compliant,
and the reason which governs it
has in itself no cause for doing evil,
for it has no malice,
nor does it do evil to anything,
nor is anything harmed by it.
But all things are made and perfected
according to this reason.
Let it make no difference to thee
whether thou art cold or warm,
if thou art doing thy duty,
and whether thou art drowsy
or satisfied with sleep,
and whether ill-spoken of
or praised.
For it is one of the acts of life,
this act by which we die,
it is sufficient then,
in this act also,
to do well what we have in hand.
Look within,
and all existing things soon change,
and they will either be reduced to vapor,
if indeed all substance is one,
or they will be dispersed.
The reason which governs
knows what its own disposition is
and what it does
and on what material it works.
The best way of avenging thyself
is not to become like the wrong-doer.
Take pleasure in one thing and rest in it
in passing from one social act
to another social act,
thinking of God.
The ruling principle
is that which rouses and turns itself,
and while it makes itself such as it is
and such as it wills to be,
it also makes everything which.
You need to add some text for me to talk.
In conformity to the nature of the universe
every single thing is accomplished,
for certainly it is not in conformity
to any other nature
that each thing is accomplished,
either a nature which externally comprehends this
or a nature which is comprehended
within this nature,
or a nature external,
and independent of this.
The universe is either a confusion
and a mutual involution of things
and a dispersion,
or it is unity and order and providence.
If, then, it is the former,
why do I desire to tarry
in a fortuitous combination of things
and such a disorder?
And why do I care about anything else
than how I shall at last become earth?
A now has been compelled by circumstances
to be disturbed in a manner.
Quickly return to thyself,
and do not continue out of tune
longer than the compulsion lasts,
for thou wilt have more mastery
over the harmony
by continually recurring to it.
If thou hadst a stepmother
and a mother at the same time,
thou wouldst be dutiful to thy stepmother,
but still thou wouldst
constantly return to thy mother.
Let the court and philosophy
now be to thee step.
Mother and mother return to philosophy
frequently and repose in her
through whom what thou meetest with
in the court appears to thee tolerable,
and thou appearst tolerable in the court.
You need to add some text for me to talk.
When we have meat before us,
and such eatables,
we receive the impression
that this is the dead body of a fish,
and this is the dead body
of a bird or of a pig.
And again, things themselves
and penetrate them,
and so we see what kind of things they are.
Just in the same way ought we to act
all through life,
and where there are things
which appear most worthy of our approbation,
we ought to lay them bare
and look at their worthlessness,
and strip them of all the words
by which they are exalted.
For outward show
is a wonderful perverter of the reason,
and when thou art most sure
that thou art employed
about things worth thy pains,
it is then that it cheats thee most.
Consider then what Crait says
of Xenocrates himself.
Most of the things which the multitude admire
are referred to objects
of the most general kind,
those which are held together
by cohesion or natural organization,
such as stones, wood,
fig-trees, vines, olives.
But those which are admired by men
who are a little more reasonable
are referred to the things
which are held together
by a living principle,
as flocks, herds.
Those which are admired by men
who are still more instructed
are the things which are held together
by a rational soul,
not, however, a universal soul,
but rational so far as it is a soul,
skilled in some art,
or expert in some other way,
or simply rational
so far as it possesses
a number of slaves.
You need to add some text
for me to talk.
But he who values rational soul,
a soul universal
and fitted for political life,
regards nothing else except this.
And above all things,
he keeps his soul in a condition
and in an activity,
conformable to reason and social life.
And he cooperates to this end
with those who are of the same kind
as himself.
Some things are hurrying into existence,
and others are hurrying out of it.
And of that which is coming into existence,
part is already extinguished
in this flowing stream then
on which there is no abiding
what is there of the things
which hurry by
on which a man would set a high price.
It would be just as if a man
should fall in love
with one of the sparrows
which fly by.
Something of this kind
is the very life of every man,
like the exhalation of the blood
and the respiration of the air.
For such as it is,
to have once drawn in the air,
and to have given it back,
which we do every moment.
Just the same is it
with the whole respiratory power
which thou didst receive
at thy birth yesterday
and the day before,
it back to the element
from which thou didst first draw it.
You need to add some text
for me to talk.
Neither is transpiration,
as in plants,
a thing to be valued,
nor respiration,
as in domesticated animals
and wild beasts,
nor the receiving of impressions
by the appearances of things,
nor being moved by desires
as puppets by strings,
nor assembling in herds,
nor in being nourished by food.
For this is just like
the act of separating and parting.
What then is worth being valued?
To be received with clapping of hands.
Neither must we value
the clapping of tongues
for the praise which comes from the many
is a clapping of tongues.
This, in my opinion,
to move thyself
and to restrain thyself
in conformity to thy proper constitution,
to which end both all employments
and arts lead.
For every art aims at this,
that the thing which has been made
should be adapted to the work
for which it has been made,
and both the vine-planter
who looks after the vine
and the horse-breaker.
But the education
and the teaching of youth
aim at something.
In this, then,
is the value of the education
and the teaching.
Then thou wilt be neither free
nor sufficient
for thy own happiness,
nor without passion.
For of necessity
thou must be envious,
jealous,
and suspicious of those
who can take away those things
and plot against those
who have that which is valued by thee.
Of necessity
a man must be altogether
in a state of perturbation
who wants any of these things,
and besides,
he must often find fault with the gods.
But to reverence and honor thy own mind
will make thee content with thyself
and in harmony with society
and in agreement with the gods,
that is, praising all that they give
and have ordered.
Above, below, all around
are the movements of the elements.
But the motion of virtue
is in none of these.
It is something more divine,
and advancing by a way
hardly observed,
it goes happily on its road,
how strangely men act.
They will not praise those
who are living at the same time
and living with and themselves.
But to be themselves,
but to be themselves
praised by posterity,
by those whom they have never seen
or ever will see,
this they set much value on.
But this is very much the same
as if thou shouldest be grieved
because those who have lived before thee
did not praise thee.
If a thing is difficult
to be accomplished by thyself,
do not think that it is impossible for man.
But if anything is possible for man
and conformable to his nature,
think that this can be attained
by thyself too.
In the gymnastic exercises
suppose that a man has torn thee
with his nails
and by dashing against thy head
has inflicted a wound.
Well, we neither show
any signs of vexation,
nor are we offended,
nor do we suspect him afterwards
as a treacherous fellow.
And yet we are on our guard against him,
not however as an enemy,
nor yet with suspicion.
But something like this,
let thy behavior be
in all the other parts of life.
Let us overlook many things
in those who are like
antagonists in the gymnasium.
For it is in our power, as I said,
to get out of the way
and to have no suspicion nor hatred.
If any man is able to convince me
and show me that I do not think
or act right,
I will gladly change,
for I seek the truth
by which no man was ever injured.
But he is injured who abides
in his error and ignorance.
I do my duty,
other things trouble me not,
for they are either things without life
or things without reason
or things that have rambled
and know not the way.
As to the animals which have no reason
and generally all things and objects,
do thou, since thou hast reason
and they have none,
make use of them
with an ingenuous and liberal spirit,
but towards human beings,
as they have reason,
behave in a social spirit.
Alexander the Macedonian
and his groom by death
were brought to the same state,
for either they were received
among the same seminal principles
of the universe,
or they were alike dispersed
among the atoms.
Consider how many things
in the same indivisible time
take place in each of us.
Things which concern the body
and things which concern the soul.
If any man should propose to thee
the question how the name Antoninus
is written,
wouldst thou with the straining
of the voice utter each letter?
What then, if they grow angry,
wilt thou be angry too?
Wilt thou not go on with composure
and number every letter?
Just so, then in this life
also remember that every duty
is made up of certain parts.
These it is thy duty to observe
and without being disturbed
or showing anger towards
those who are angry with thee
to go on thy way
and finish that which is set before thee.
How cruel it is not to allow men
to strive after the things
which appear to them
to be suitable to their nature
and profitable.
For they are certainly moved
towards things because they suppose
them to be suitable to their nature
and profitable to them.
But knit is not so.
Teach them then
and show them without being angry.
Death is a cessation of the impressions
through the senses
and of the pulling of the strings
which move the appetites
and of the discursive movements.
It is a shame for the soul to be first
to give way in this life
when thy body does not give way.
Take care that thou art not made
into a Caesar,
that thou art not died with this die,
for such things happen.
Keep thyself then simple,
good, pure, serious,
free from affectation.
You need to add some text for me to talk.
Remember his constancy in every act
which was conformable to reason
and his evenness in all things
and his piety
and the serenity of his countenance
and his sweetness
and his disregard of empty fame
and his efforts to understand things
and how he would never let anything pass
without having first
most carefully examined it
and clearly.
You need to add some text for me to talk.
Understood it
and how he bore with those
who blamed him unjustly
without blaming them in return,
how he did nothing in a hurry
and how he listened not to Calamnes
and how exact an examiner
of manners and actions he was.
And patient and how he was able
on account of his sparing diet
to hold out to the evening.
Opinions and the pleasure that he had
when any man showed him anything better
and how religious he was
without superstition.
Reverence the gods and help men.
Short is life.
Return to thy sober senses
and call thyself back.
I consist of a little body
and a soul.
Now to this little body
all things are indifferent
for it is not able to perceive differences.
But whatever things are
the works of its own activity
all these are in its power.
And of these however
only those which are done
with reference to the present
for as to the future
and the past activities of the mind
even these are for the present
indifferent.
Neither the labor which the hand does
nor that of the foot
is contrary to nature.
So long as the foot does the foot's work
and the hand the hands.
So then neither to a man as a man
is his labor.
Contrary to nature.
So long as it does the things of a man
but if the labor is not contrary
to his nature
neither is it an evil to him.
Dost thou not see how the handy craftsmen
accommodate themselves
up to a certain point to those
who are not skilled in their craft.
Nevertheless they cling to the reason
the principles of their art.
Is it not strange if the architect
and the physician shall have more respect
to the reason
the principles of their own arts
than man to his own reason
which is common to him and the gods.
Asia, Europe are corners of the universe
all the sea a drop in the universe
ethos a little clod of the universe
all the present time is a point in eternity.
All things are little changeable perishable
all things come from thence
from that universal ruling power
either directly proceeding
or by way of sequence.
And accordingly the lion's gaping jaws
and that which is poisonous
and every harmful thing
as a thorn as mud
are after products of the grand and beautiful.
Do not then imagine
that they are of another kind
from that which thou dost venerate
but form a just opinion
of the source of all.
He who has seen present things
has seen all
both everything
which has taken place from all eternity
and everything
which will be for time without end.
For all things are of one kin
and of one form.
Frequently consider the connection
of all things in the universe
and their relation to one another.
For in a manner all things
are implicated with one another
and all in this way
are friendly to one another.
For one thing comes in order after another
and this is by virtue
of the act of movement
and mutual conspiration
and the unity of thee.
Adapt thyself to the things
with which thy lot has been cast
and the man among whom
thou hast received thy portion.
Love them but do it truly, sincerely.
Every instrument, tool, vessel,
vessel, if it does that
for which it has been made, is well.
But in the things which are held
and together by nature
there is within
and there abides in them
the power which made them.
Wherefore the more is it fit
to reverence this power
and to think that
if thou dost live and act
according to its will,
everything in thee
is in conformity to intelligence.
You need to add some text
for me to talk.
Whatever of the things
which are not within thy power
thou shalt suppose to be good for thee
or evil.
It must of necessity be that.
If such a bad thing befall thee
or the loss of such a good thing
thou wilt blame the gods
and hate men too.
Those who are the cause
of the misfortune or the loss
or those who are suspected
of being likely to be the cause.
And indeed we do much injustice
because we make a difference
between these things.
And thus also in the universe
the things which belong to it
are in conformity to intelligence.
But if we judge only those things
which are in our power
to be good or bad
there remains no reason
either for finding fault with God
or standing in a hostile attitude to man.
We are all working together
to one end,
some with knowledge and design
and others without knowing
what they do.
As men also when they are asleep
of whom it is Heraclitus I think
who says that they are
laborers and cooperators
in the things which take place
in the universe.
But men cooperate
after different fashions
and even those cooperate abundantly.
Who find fault with what happens
and those who try to oppose it
and to hinder it.
For the universe had need
even of such man as these.
It remains then for thee to understand
among what kind of workman
thou places thyself.
For he who rules all things
will certainly make a right use of thee
and he will receive thee
among some part of the co.
But be not thou such a part
as the mean and ridiculous verse
in the play
which Chrysippus speaks of.
And does the sun undertake
to do the work of the rain?
Or Isculapius the work
of the fruit bearer, the earth?
And how is it with respect
to each of the stars?
Are they not different
and yet they work together
to the same end?
If the gods have determined about me
and about the things
which must happen to me
they have determined well.
For it is not easy even
to imagine a deity
without forethought.
And as to doing me harm
why should they have any desire?
For what advantage would result to them
from this or to the whole
which is the special object
of their providence?
But if they have not
determined about me individually
they have certainly determined
about the whole at least.
And the things which happen
by way of sequence
in this general arrangement
I ought to accept
with pleasure and to be.
You need to add some text
for me to talk.
But if they determine
about nothing
which it is wicked to believe
or if we do believe it
let us neither sacrifice
nor pray nor swear by them
nor do anything else
which we do
as if the gods were present
and lived with us.
But if however the gods determine
about none of the things
which concern us
I am able to determine
about myself
and I can.
Inquire about that
which is useful
and that is useful to every man
which is conformable
to his own constitution and nature.
But my nature is rational
and social
and my city and country
so far as I am Antoninus
is Rome.
But so far as I am a man
it is the world.
The things then
which are useful to these cities
are alone useful to me.
Whatever happens to every man
this is for the interest
of the universal
this might be sufficient.
But further thou wilt
observe this also
as a general truth.
If thou dost observe
that whatever is profitable
to any man
is profitable also
to other men.
But let the word profitable
be taken here
in the common sense
as said
of things of the middle kind
neither good nor bad.
As it happens to thee
in the amphitheatre
and such places
that the continual sight
of the same things
and the uniformity
make the spectacle wearisome
so it is in the whole of life
for all things above
below are the same.
How long then?
Think continually
that all kinds of men
and of all kinds of pursuits
and of all nations are dead
so that thy thoughts come down
even to Philistian
and Phoebus
and Oregonian.
Now turn thy thoughts
to the other kinds of men.
You need to add some text
for me to talk.
To that place then
we must remove
where there are so many
great orators
and so many noble philosophers
Heraclitus
Pythagoras
Socrates
so many heroes
of former days
and so many generals
after them
and tyrants
besides these
Eudoxus
Hipparchus
Confident
mockers even
of the perishable
and ephemeral life of man
as Manipus
and such as are like him.
As to all these
consider that they have long
been in the dust.
What harm then is this to them
and what to those
whose names are altogether unknown?
One thing here
is worth a great deal
to pass thy life
in truth and justice
with a benevolent disposition
even to liars
and unjust men.
When thou wishest
to delight thyself
think of the virtues
of those who live with thee
for instance
the activity of one
and the modesty of another
and the liberality of a third
and some other good quality
of a fourth
for nothing delights so much
as the examples of the virtues
when they are exhibited
in the morals
of those who live with us
and present themselves
in abundance
as far as is possible.
Thou art not dissatisfied
I suppose
because thou weigh'st
only so many litre
and not three hundred.
Let us try to persuade the men
but act even against their will
when the principles of justice
lead that way.
If however any man
by using force
stands in thy way
betake thyself
to contentment
and tranquility
and at the same time
employ the hindrance
towards the exercise
of some other virtue.
Reservation
that thou dost not desire
to do impossibilities
what then didst thou desire?
Some such effort is this
but thou attainest thy object
if the things to which
thou wast moved
are accomplished.
He who loves fame
considers another man's activity
to be his own good
and he who loves pleasure
his own sensations
but he who has understanding
considers his own acts
to be his own good.
It is in our power
to have no opinion
about a thing.
That which is not good
for this form
neither is it good for the bee.
If sailors abused the helmsman
or the sick, the doctor
would they listen to anybody else
or how could the helmsman
secure the safety
of those in the ship
or the doctor
the health of those
whom he attends?
How many together
with whom I came into the world
are already gone out.
To the jaundiced honey
tastes bitter
and to those bitten
by mad dogs
water causes fear
and to little children
the ball is a fine thing.
Why then am I angry?
Does thou think
that a false opinion
has less power
than the bile in the jaundiced
or the poison in him
who is bitten by a mad dog?
No man will hinder thee
from living according
to the reason
of thy own nature.
Nothing will happen to thee
contrary to the reason
of the universal nature.
What kind of people
are those who men wish to please?
And for what objects?
How soon will time
cover all things
and how many
it has covered already?
Book 7
What is badness?
It is that which
thou hast often seen.
And on the occasion
of everything which happens
keep this in mind
that it is that
which thou hast often seen.
Everywhere up and down
thou wilt find the same things
with which the old histories
are filled
those of the middle ages
and those of our own day
with which cities
and houses are filled now.
How can our principles
become dead
unless the impressions, thoughts
which correspond to them
are extinguished?
But it is in thy power
continuously
to fan these thoughts
into a flame.
I can have that opinion
about anything
which I ought to have.
If I can, why am I disturbed?
Look at things again
as thou didst use
to look at end them.
For in this
consists the recovery
of thy life.
The idle business of show
plays on the stage
flocks of sheep, herds,
exercises with spears,
a bone cast to little dogs,
a bit of bread into fish ponds,
labourings of ants
and burden carrying,
runnings about
of frightened little mice,
puppets.
It is thy duty then
in the midst of such things
to show good humour
and not a proud air,
to understand, however,
that every man is worth
just so much
as the things are worth
about which he busies himself.
In discourse,
thou must attend
to what is said,
and in every movement
thou must observe
what is doing.
Is my understanding
sufficient for this or not?
If it is sufficient,
I use it for the work
as an instrument
given by the universal nature.
But if it is not sufficient,
then either I retire
from the work
and give way to him
who is able to do it better,
unless there be some reason
why I ought not to do so,
or I do it as well as I can,
taking to help.
Me, the man who,
with the aid of my ruling principle,
can do what is now fit
and useful for the general good,
for whatsoever,
either by myself
or with another,
I can do,
ought to be directed
to this only,
to that which is useful
and well suited to society.
How many,
after being celebrated by fame,
have been given up to oblivion,
and how many who have celebrated
the fame of others
have long been dead?
Be not ashamed to be helped,
for it is thy business
to do thy duty,
like a soldier in the assault
on a town.
Let not future things disturb thee,
for thou wilt come to them,
if it shall be necessary,
having with thee
the same reason
which now thou usest
for present things.
For things have been coordinated,
and they combine
to form the same universe,
order.
For there is one universe,
made up of all things,
and one God
who pervades all things,
and one substance,
and one law,
one common reason
in all intelligent animals.
Everything material soon disappears
in the substance of the whole,
and everything formal,
causal,
is very soon taken back
into the universal reason,
and the memory of everything
is very soon overwhelmed in time.
To the rational animal,
the same act is according to nature,
and according to reason.
Be thou erect,
or be made erect.
Just as it is
with the members in those bodies
which are united in one,
so it is with rational beings
which exist separate,
for they have been constituted
for one cooperation,
and the perception of this
will be more apparent to thee.
If thou often say'st to thyself,
that I am a member
of the system of rational beings.
But if, using the letter R,
thou say'st that thou art a part,
thou dost not yet love men
from thy heart.
Beneficence does not yet delight thee
for its own sake.
Thou still do'st it barely
as a thing of,
and let there fall externally.
What will on the parts
which can feel the effects
of this fall?
For those parts which have felt
will complain,
if they choose.
But I,
unless I think
that what has happened
is an evil,
and it is in my power
not to think so,
whatever any one does or says,
I must be good.
Just as if the gold,
or the emerald,
or the purple
were always saying this,
whatever any one does or says,
I must be emerald
and keep my color.
The ruling faculty
does not disturb itself,
I mean,
does not frighten itself,
or cause itself pain.
But, if any one else
can frighten or pain it,
let him do so.
For the faculty itself
will not,
by its own opinion,
turn itself into such ways.
Let the body itself take care,
if it can,
that it suffer nothing,
and let it speak,
if it suffers.
But the soul itself,
that which is subject
to fear,
to pain,
which has completely
the power of forming
an opinion about these things,
will suffer nothing,
for it will never deviate
into such a judgment.
The leading principle
in itself
wants nothing,
unless it makes a want
for itself,
and therefore,
it is both free
from perturbation,
and unimpeded,
if it does not disturb
and impede itself.
What then art thou doing here,
O imagination?
Go away,
I entreat thee by the gods,
as thou didst come,
for I want thee not.
Is any man afraid of change?
Why?
What can take place
without change?
What then is more pleasing,
or more suitable
to the universal nature?
And canst thou take a bath,
unless the wood
undergoes a change?
And canst thou be nourished,
unless the food
undergoes an inchange?
Through the universal substance,
as through a furious torrent,
all bodies are carried,
being by their nature
united with,
and cooperating with,
the whole,
as the parts of our body
with one another.
And let the same thought
occur to thee
with reference
to every man and thing.
One thing only troubles me,
lest I should do something
which the constitution of man
does not allow,
or in the way which
it does not allow,
or what it does not allow now,
near is thy forgetfulness
of all things,
and near the forgetfulness
of thee by all.
It is peculiar to man
to love even those
who do wrong.
And this happens,
if, when they do wrong,
it occurs to thee
that they are kinsmen,
and that they do wrong
through ignorance
and unintentionally,
and that soon
both of you will die.
Wrongdoer has done thee no harm,
for he has not made
thy ruling faculty
worse than it was before.
The universal nature
out of the universal substance,
as if it were wax,
now molds a horse,
and when it has broken this up,
it uses the material for a tree,
then for a man,
then for something else,
and each of these things
subsists for a very short time.
But it is no hardship
for the vessel to be broken up,
just as there was none
in its being fastened together.
A scowling look
is altogether unnatural,
when it is often assumed
the result is that
all comeliness dies,
and at last
is so completely extinguished
that it cannot be again
lighted up at all.
Try to conclude,
from this very fact,
that it is contrary to reason.
For if,
even the perception
of doing wrong shall depart,
what reason is there
for living any longer?
Nature which governs the whole
will soon change all things
which thou seest,
and out of their substance
will make other things,
and again other things
from the substance of them.
In, when a man has done
thee any wrong,
immediately consider
with what opinion
about good or evil
he has done wrong.
For when thou hast seen this,
thou wilt pity him,
and wilt neither wonder
nor be angry.
For either thou thyself
thinkest the same thing
to be good,
that he does,
or another thing
of the same kind,
it is thy duty then
to pardon him.
Think not so much
of what thou hast not
as of what thou hast,
but of the things
which thou hast select the best,
and then reflect
how eagerly
they would have been sought.
If thou hast them not,
at the same time, however,
take care that thou dost not,
through being so pleased with them,
accustom thyself
to overvalue them,
so as to be disturbed,
if ever,
retire into thyself.
The rational principle
which rules has this nature,
that it is content with itself
when it does what is just,
and so secures tranquility.
Wipe out the imagination.
Stop the pulling of the strings.
Confine thyself to the present.
Understand well
what happens either to thee
or to another.
Divide and distribute
every object into the causal,
informal,
and the material.
Direct thy attention
to what is said.
Let thy understanding
enter into the things
that are doing,
and the things which do them.
Adorn thyself with simplicity
and modesty
and with indifference
towards the things which lie
between virtue and vice.
Love mankind.
About pain,
the pain which is intolerable
carries us off.
But that which lasts
a long time
is tolerable.
But the parts
which are harmed by pain,
let them,
if they can,
give their opinion about it.
About fame,
look at the minds
of those who seek fame.
Observe what they are,
and what kind of things they avoid,
and what kind of things they pursue.
And consider that,
as the heaps of sand piled
on one another
hide the former sands,
so in life the events
which go before
are soon covered
by those which come after.
From Plato,
the man who has
an elevated mind
and takes a view of all time
and of all substance,
dost thou suppose it possible
for him to think
that human life
is anything great?
It is not possible,
he said.
Such a man then will think
that death also is no evil.
Certainly not.
From Antisthenes
it is royal to do good
and to be abused.
It is a base thing
for the countenance
to be obedient
and to regulate
and compose itself
as the mind commands,
and for the mind
not to be regulated
and composed by itself.
It is not right
to vex ourselves at things,
for they care not about it.
To the immortal gods
and us give joy.
For the good is with me,
and the just.
No joining others
in their wailing,
no violent emotion.
From Plato,
but I would make this man
a sufficient answer,
which is this.
Thou sayest not well,
if thou thinkest
that a man
who is good
for anything at all
ought to compute
the hazard of life
or death,
and should not rather
look to this
only in all that.
He does,
whether he is doing
what is just or unjust,
and the works of a good
or a bad man.
For thus it is,
man of Athens,
in truth,
wherever a man
has placed himself
thinking at the best place for him,
or has been placed
by a commander.
There, in my opinion,
he ought to stay
and to abide the hazard,
taking nothing
into the reckoning,
either death
or anything else
before the baseness
of deserting his post.
You need to add some text
for me to talk.
N.
But, my good friend,
reflect whether that
which is noble and good
is not something different
from saving and being saved,
for as to a man
living such or such a time,
at least one
who is really a man,
consider if this is not a thing
to be dismissed
from the thoughts,
and there must be
no love of life.
But as to these matters
a man must entrust.
Damn to the deity,
and believe
what the women say,
that no man
can escape his destiny.
The next inquiry
being how he may best live
the time that he has to live.
Look round at the courses
of the stars,
as if thou wert
going along with them,
and constantly consider
the changes of the elements
into one another,
for such thoughts
purge away the filth
of the Terran life.
You need to add some text
for me to talk.
This is a fine saying of Plato,
that he who is discoursing
about men
should look also
at earthly things,
as if he viewed them
from some higher place,
should look at them
in their assemblies,
armies,
agricultural labors,
marriages,
treaties,
births,
deaths,
noise of the courts of justice,
desert places,
various nations of barbarians,
feasts,
lamentations,
markets,
a mixture of all things,
and an orderly combination
of contraries.
Consider the past,
such great changes
of political supremacies,
thou mayst foresee also
the things which will be,
for they will certainly be
of like form,
and it is not possible
that they should deviate
from the order of the things
which take place now.
Accordingly,
to have contemplated human life
for forty years
is the same as to have.
For what more wilt thou see,
that which is grown
from the earth to the earth,
but that which is sprung
from heavenly seed,
back to the heavenly realms
returns.
This is either
a dissolution
of the mutual involution
of the atoms,
or a similar indispersion
of the unsentient elements,
with food and drinks
and cunning magic arts
turning the channel's course
to escape from death.
Another may be more expert
in casting his opponent,
but he is not more social,
nor more modest,
nor better disciplined
to meet all that happens,
nor more considerate with.
Where any work
can be done conformably
to the reason which is common
to gods and men,
there we have nothing to fear.
For where we are able
to get profit
by means of the activity
which is successful
and proceeds according
to our constitution,
there no harm
is to be suspected.
Everywhere and at all times
it is in thy power
piously to acquiesce
in thy present condition,
and to behave justly
to those who are about thee,
and to exert thy skill
upon thy present thoughts,
that nothing shall steal into them
without being well examined.
Do not look around thee
to discover other men's
ruling principles,
but look straight to this,
to what nature leads thee,
both the universal nature
through the things
which happen to thee,
and thy own nature
through the acts
which must be done by thee.
But every being ought to do
that which is according
to its constitution,
and all other things
have been constituted
for the sake of rational beings,
just as among irrational things,
the inferior
for the sake of the superior.
But the rational,
for the sake of one another.
You need to add some text
for me to talk.
And the second is not to yield
to the persuasions of the body,
for it is the peculiar office
of the rational
and intelligent motion
to circumscribe itself,
and never to be overpowered,
either by the motion
of the senses
or of the appetites,
for both are animal.
But the intelligent motion
claims superiority.
The prime principle then
in man's constitution
is the in-social,
and with good reason,
for it is formed by nature
to use all of them.
Let then the ruling principle
holding fast to these things
go straight on,
and it has what is its own.
Love that only which happens
to thee
and is spun with the thread
of thy destiny,
for what is more suitable,
in everything which happens,
keep before thy eyes
those to whom
the same things happened,
and how they were vexed
and treated them
as strange things,
and found fault with them,
and now where are they?
Why then dost thou too
choose to act in the same way?
And why dost thou not leave
these agitations
which are foreign to nature,
to those who cause them,
and those who are moved by them?
And why art thou not
altogether intent
upon the right way
of making use
of the things
which happen to thee?
For then thou wilt use them well,
and they will be a material
for thee to work on.
Only attend to thyself,
and resolve to be a good man
in every act
which thou doest.
And remember,
the body ought to be compact,
and to show no new regularity
either in motion or attitude,
for what the mind shows in the face,
by maintaining in it
the expression of intelligence
and propriety,
that ought to be required
also in the whole body,
but all of these things
should be observed
without affectation.
The art of life is more like
the wrestler's art
than the dancer's,
in respect of this,
that it should stand ready
and firm
to meet onsets
which are sudden and unexpected.
Constantly observe
who those are,
whose approbation
thou wishest to have,
and what ruling principles
they possess.
For then thou wilt neither blame
those who offend involuntarily,
nor wilt thou want
their approbation,
if thou lookest to the sources
of their opinions and appetites.
Every soul, the philosopher says,
is involuntarily deprived of truth.
Consequently, in the same way,
it is deprived of justice
and temperance
and benevolence
and everything of the kind.
In every pain
let this thought be present,
that there is no dishonor in it,
nor does it make
the governing intelligence worse,
for it does not damage
the intelligence.
You need to add some text
for me to talk.
Indeed, in the case of most pains,
let this remark of Epicurus aid thee.
That pain is neither intolerable
nor everlasting,
if thou bearest in mind
that it has its limits,
and if thou addest nothing
to it in imagination.
And remember this, too,
that we do not perceive
that many things
which are disagreeable to us
are the same as pain,
such as excessive drowsiness
and the being scorched by heat
and the having no appetite.
When then thou art discontented
about any of these things,
say to thyself
that thou art not yielding to pain.
You need to add some text
for me to talk,
for it is not enough
that Socrates died
a more noble death
and disputed more skillfully
with the sophists,
and passed the night in the cold
with more endurance,
and that when he was bid
to arrest Leon of Salamis,
he considered it more noble
to refuse,
and that he walked
in a swaggering way in the streets.
Though as to this fact
one may have great
what kind of a soul it was
that Socrates possessed,
and if he was able to be content
with being just towards men
and pious towards the gods,
neither idly vexed
on account of men's villainy,
nor yet making himself a slave
to any man's ignorance,
nor enduring it as intolerable,
nor allowing his understanding
to sympathize with the affects
of the miserable flesh.
Nature has not so mingled
the intelligence
with the composition of the body,
as not to have allowed thee
the power of circumscribing thyself,
and of bringing under subjection
to thyself
all that is thy own,
for it is very possible
to be a divine man,
and to be recognized as such
by no one.
Always bear this in mind.
And another thing too,
that very little indeed
is necessary for living
a happy life.
And because thou hast despaired
of becoming a dialectician
and skilled in the knowledge of nature,
do not for this reason
renounce the hope
of being both free and modest,
and social, and obedient to God.
It is in thy power
to live free from all compulsion,
in the greatest tranquillity of mind,
even if all the world
cry out against thee
as much as they choose.
NAND!
For what hinders the mind,
in the midst of all this,
from maintaining itself
in tranquillity,
and in a just judgment
of all surrounding things,
and in a ready use
of the objects
which are presented to it,
so that the judgment may say
to the thing which falls
under its observation,
This thou art,
in substance,
reality.
You need to add some text
for me to talk.
My est appear to be
of a different kind,
and the use shall say to that
which falls under the hand,
Thou art the thing
that I was seeking.
For to me that which presents itself
is always a material for virtue,
both rational and political,
and, in a word,
for the exercise of art,
which belongs to man or God.
For everything which happens
has a relationship
either to God or man,
and is neither new
nor difficult to handle,
but usual and apt matter
to work on.
The perfection of moral character
consists in this,
in passing every day as the last,
and in being neither
violently excited,
nor torpid,
nor playing the hypocrite.
The gods who are immortal
are not vexed
because during so long a time
they must tolerate continually.
Men such as they are,
and so many of them bad.
But thou,
who art destined to end so soon,
art thou wearied
of enduring the bad,
and this too,
when thou art one of them.
Whatever the rational
and political, social faculty
finds to be neither intelligent
nor social,
it properly judges
to be inferior to itself.
And when thou hast done a good act
and another has received it,
why dost thou look
for a third thing
besides these,
as fools do,
either to have the reputation
of having done a good act,
or to obtain a return?
No man is tired of receiving
what is useful.
But it is useful
to act according to nature.
Do not then be tired
of receiving what is useful
by doing it to others.
But now,
either everything that takes place
comes by way of consequence
or continuity,
or even the chief things
towards which
the ruling power of the universe
directs its own movement
are governed
by no rational principle.
If this is remembered,
it will make thee more tranquil
in many things.
Book 8
This reflection also tends
to the removal
of the desire of empty fame,
that it is no longer
in thy power
to have lived
the whole of thy life,
or at least thy life
from thy youth upwards,
like a philosopher.
But both to many others
and to thyself
it is plain that thou,
thou hast fallen
into disorder then
so that it is no longer
easy for thee
to get the reputation
of a philosopher,
and thy plan of life
also opposes it.
If then thou hast truly seen
where the matter lies,
throw away the thought
how thou shalt seem to others,
and be content
if thou shalt live
the rest of thy life
in such wise
as thy nature wills.
Observe then what it wills,
and let nothing else
distract thee,
for thou hast had experience
of many wanderings
without having found
happiness anywhere,
not in syllogisms,
nor in wealth,
nor in reputation,
nor in enjoyment,
nor anywhere.
Where is it then?
In doing what man's
nature requires.
How then shall a man do
in this?
If he has principles
from which come
his effects
and his acts,
what principles?
Those which relate
to good and bad,
the belief that
there is nothing good
for man
which does not make
him just,
temperate,
manly,
free,
and that there is
nothing bad
which does not.
On the occasion
of every act,
ask thyself
how is this
with respect to me?
Shall I repent of it?
A little time,
and I am dead,
and all is gone.
What more do I seek
if what I am now doing
is work of an
intelligent living being
and a social being
and one who is under
the same law with God?
Alexander and Gaius
and Pompeius,
what are they
in comparison
with Diogenes
and Heraclitus
and Socrates?
But as to the others,
how many things
had they to care for
and to how many things
were they slaves?
Consider that men
will do the same things
nevertheless,
even though thou
shouldst burst.
This is the chief thing.
Be not perturbed,
for all things
are according
to the nature
of the universal,
and in a little time
thou wilt be
nobody
and nowhere.
In the next place,
having fixed thy eyes
steadily on thy business,
look at it,
and at the same time,
remembering that
it is thy duty
to be a good man,
and what man's
nature demands,
do that
without turning aside.
The nature of the universal
has this work to do,
to remove to that place
the things which are in this,
to change them,
to take them away.
You need to add some text
for me to talk.
Every nature is contented
with itself
when it goes on its way well,
and a rational nature
goes on its way well.
When in its thoughts
it ascends to nothing
false or uncertain,
and when it directs
its movements
to social acts only,
and when it confines
its desires and aversions
to the things
which are in its power,
everything that is assigned to it
by the common nature,
you need to add some text
for me to talk.
For of this common nature
every particular nature
is a part,
as the nature of the leaf
is a part of the nature
of the plant,
intelligent and just,
since it gives to everything
in equal portions,
and according to its worth,
times, substance,
cause, form,
activity,
and incident.
All things are familiar to us,
but the distribution of them
still remains the same.
But examine,
not to discover
that any one thing
compared with any other single thing
is equal in all respects,
but by taking all the parts
together of one thing
and comparing them
with all the parts together
of another.
Thou hast not leisure
or ability to read,
but thou hast leisure
or ability to check arrogance.
Thou hast leisure
to be superior
to pleasure and pain.
Thou hast leisure
to be superior
to love of fame,
and not to be vexed
at stupid and ungrateful people,
nay, even to care for them.
Let no man any longer
hear thee finding fault
with the court life
or with thy own,
but no such man
would ever repent
of having refused
any sensual pleasure.
Pleasure, then,
is neither good nor useful.
This thing,
what is it in itself,
in its own constitution?
What is its substance
and material?
And what its causal nature
or form?
And what is it doing
in the world?
And how long does it subsist?
When thou risest
from sleep with reluctance,
remember that it is
according to thy constitution
and according to human nature
to perform social acts.
But sleeping is common also
to irrational animals.
But that which is according
to each individual's nature
is also more peculiarly
its own and more suitable
to its nature,
and indeed also more agreeable.
Constantly and,
if it be possible,
on the occasion of every
impression on the soul,
apply to it the principles
of physic, of ethic,
and of dialectic.
Whatever man thou meetest with,
immediately say to thyself,
What opinions has this man
about good and bad?
For if, with respect to
pleasure and pain
and the causes of each,
and with respect to fame
and ignominy,
death and life,
he has such and such opinions,
will seem nothing wonderful
or strange to me.
Remember that as it is ashamed
to be surprised
if the fig tree produces figs,
so it is to be surprised
if the world produces
such and such things,
of which it is productive.
Remember that,
to change thy opinion
and to follow him
who corrects thy error
is as consistent with freedom
as it is to persist
in thy error.
For it is thy own,
and the activity which is exerted,
according to thy own movement
and judgment,
and indeed,
according to thy own
understanding too.
If a thing is in thy own power,
why dost thou do it?
But if it is in the power
of another,
whom dost thou blame?
The atoms,
chance,
or the gods?
Both are foolish.
For if thou canst,
correct that which is the cause.
But if thou canst not do this,
correct at least the thing itself.
But if thou canst not do even this,
for nothing should be done
without a purpose.
That which is died
falls not out of the universe.
And these too change,
and they murmur not.
Everything exists for some end,
a horse,
a vine.
Why dost thou wonder?
Even the sun will say,
I am for some purpose,
and the rest of the gods
will say the same.
For what purpose?
Then art thou.
What good is it then
for the ball to be thrown up?
Or harm for it to come down,
or even to have fallen?
And what good is it to the bubble
while it holds together?
Or what harm when it is burst?
Turn it, the body,
inside out,
and see what kind of thing it is.
And when it has grown old,
what kind of thing it becomes,
and when it is diseased.
Short-lived are both
the praiser and the praised.
And the rememberer
and the remembered.
And all this in a nook
of this part of the world.
And not even here do all agree,
no, not any one with.
Attend to the matter
which is before thee,
whether it is an opinion,
or an act, or a word.
Thou suffer'st this justly,
for thou choosest rather
to become good to-morrow
than to be good to-day.
I do it with reference
to the good of mankind.
Does anything happen to me?
I receive it,
and refer it to the gods,
and the source of all things,
from which all that happens
is derived.
Such as bathing appears to thee,
oil, sweat, dirt, filthy water,
all things disgusting,
so is every part of life
and everything.
Lucilla saw Verus die,
and then Lucilla died.
Secunda saw Maximus die,
and then Secunda died.
Epitensionist saw Diotimus die,
and Epitensionist died.
Such is everything.
Seller saw Hadrian die,
and then Seller died,
all ephemeral, dead long ago.
Some indeed have not been remembered
even for a short time,
and others have become
the heroes of fables,
and again others have disappeared
even from fables.
Remember this then,
that this little compound,
thy self, must either be dissolved,
or thy poor breath
must be extinguished,
or be removed
and placed elsewhere.
It is satisfaction to a man
to do the proper works of a man.
Now it is a proper work of a man
to be in benevolent to his own kind,
to despise the movements of the senses,
to form a just judgment
of plausible appearances,
and to take a survey
of the nature of the universe
and of the things which happen in it.
There are three relations
between thee and other things,
the one to the body
which surrounds thee,
the second to the divine cause
from which all things come to all,
and the third to those who live with thee.
Pain is either an evil to the body,
then let the body say
what it thinks of it,
or to the soul.
But it is in the power of the soul
to maintain its own serenity
and tranquility,
and not to think
that pain is an evil.
For every judgment
and movement and desire
and aversion is within,
and no evil ascends so high.
Wipe out thy imaginations
by often saying to thyself,
Now it is in my power
to let no badness be in this soul,
nor desire,
nor any perturbation at all.
Remember this power
which thou hast from nature.
Speak both in the Senate
and to every man,
whoever he may be,
appropriately,
not with any affectation,
use plain discourse.
Augustus's court,
wife, daughter,
descendants, ancestors, sister,
Agrippa, kinsmen,
intimates, friends,
Aureus, Messinus,
physicians and sacrificing priests,
the whole court is.
Then turn to the rest,
not considering the death
of a single man,
but of a whole race,
as of the Pompeii,
and that which is inscribed
on the tombs,
the last of his race.
Then consider what trouble
those before them have had
that they might leave a successor.
And then, that of necessity,
some one must be the last.
Again here,
consider the death of a whole race.
In it is thy duty
to order thy life well
in every single act,
and if every act does its duty
as far as is possible,
be content,
and no one is able to hinder thee
so that each act
shall not do its duty.
But something external
will stand in the way.
Nothing will stand in the way
of thy acting justly,
and soberly,
and considerately.
But perhaps some other act of power
will be hindered.
Well, but, by acquiescing
in the hindrance,
and by being content
to transfer thy efforts
to that which is allowed,
another opportunity of action
is immediately put,
before thee,
in place of that which was hindered,
and one which will adapt itself
to this ordering
of which we are speaking.
Receive wealth or prosperity
without arrogance,
if thou dost ever see
a hand cut off,
or a foot,
or a head,
lying anywhere apart
from the rest of the body.
Such does a man make himself
as far as he can,
who is not content
with what happens
and separates himself from others,
or does anything unsocial.
Suppose that thou hast
detached thyself
from the natural unity,
for thou wast made by nature apart.
God has allowed this
to no other part,
after it has been separated
and cut asunder,
to come together again.
But consider the kindness
by which he has distinguished man,
for he has put it in his power
not to be separated at all
from the universal,
and when he has been separated,
he has allowed him to return
and to be united
and to resume his place.
As the nature of the universal
has given to every rational being
all the other powers that it has,
so we have received from it
this power also.
For as the universal nature
converts and fixes
in its impredestined place,
everything which stands in the way
and opposes it,
and makes such things
a part of itself,
so also the rational animal
is able to make every hindrance
its own material,
and to use it for such purposes
as it may have designed,
do not disturb thyself
by thinking of the whole of thy life.
Let not thy thoughts at once
embrace all the various troubles
which thou mayst expect
to befall thee,
but on every occasion
ask thyself,
What is there in this
which is intolerable
and past-bearing?
For thou wilt be ashamed to confess.
In the next place,
remember that neither the future
nor the past pains thee,
but only the present.
But this is reduced to a very little,
if thou only circumscribest it,
and chidest thy mind,
if it is unable to hold out
against even this.
Does panthea or pergamos
now sit by the tomb of Verus?
Does sureus or diatomus
sit by the tomb of Hadrian?
That would be ridiculous.
Well, suppose they did sit there,
would the dead be conscious of it?
And if the dead were conscious,
would they be pleased?
And if they were pleased,
would that make them immortal?
Was it not in the order of destiny
that these persons too
should first become old women
and old men,
and then die?
What then would those do
after these were dead?
All this is foul smell and blood in a bag.
If thou canst see sharp,
look and judge wisely,
says the philosopher.
In the constitution of the rational animal,
I see no virtue which is opposed to justice,
but I see a virtue which is opposed
to love of pleasure,
and that is temperance.
If thou takest away thy opinion
about that which appears to give thee pain,
thou thyself standest in imperfect security.
Who is this self?
The reason.
But if any other part of thee suffers,
let it have its own opinion about itself,
and something else also is equally an impediment
and an evil to the constitution of plans.
So then, that which is a hindrance
to the intelligence is an evil
to the intelligent nature.
Does pain or sensuous pleasure affect thee?
The senses will look to that.
If, indeed, thou wast making this effort,
absolutely, unconditionally,
or without any reservation,
certainly this obstacle is an evil
to thee considered as a rational animal.
But if thou takest into consideration
the usual course of things,
thou hast not yet been injured,
nor even impeded.
When it has been made a sphere,
it continues a sphere.
It is not fit that I should give myself pain,
for I have never intentionally given pain
even to another.
Different things delight different people,
but it is my delight to keep
the ruling faculty sound,
without turning away either from any man
or from any of the things
which happen to men.
But looking at, and receiving all
with welcome eyes, and using everything
according to its value,
see that thou secure this present time
to thyself.
For those who rather pursue posthumous fame,
do consider that the men of after time
will be exactly and such as these
whom they cannot bear now.
And what is it in any way to thee
if these men of after time
utter this or that sound,
or have this or that opinion about thee?
Take me and cast me where thou wilt,
for there I shall keep my divine part tranquil,
that is, content,
if it can feel and act conformably
to its proper constitution.
Is this change of place?
Nothing can happen to any man
which is not a human accident,
nor to an ox which is not according
to the nature of an ox,
nor to a vine which is not,
according to the nature of a vine,
nor to a stone which is not proper to a stone.
If, then, there happens to each thing,
both what is usual and natural,
why shouldst thou complain?
For the common nature brings nothing,
which may not be borne by thee.
If thou art pained by any external thing,
it is not this thing that disturbs thee,
but thy own judgment about it.
And it is in thy power to wipe out this judgment now.
But if anything in thy own disposition gives thee pain,
who hinders thee from correcting thy opinion?
And even if thou art pained,
because thou art not doing some particular thing,
which seems to thee to be right,
why dost thou not rather act than complain?
But some insuperable obstacle is in the way.
Do not be grieved, then,
for the cause of its not being done
depends not on thee.
But it is not worth while to live
if this cannot be done.
Take thy departure, then, from life contentedly,
just as he dies who is in full activity,
and well pleased too with the things which are obstacles.
Remember that the ruling faculty is invincible,
when and self-collected it is satisfied with itself,
if it does nothing, which it does not choose to do,
even if it resists from mere obstinancy.
What, then, will it be when it forms a judgment
about anything aided by reason and deliberately?
Therefore the mind which is free from passions is a citadel,
for man has nothing more secure to which he can fly.
Say nothing more to thyself
than what the first appearances report.
I see that my child is sick.
I do see, but that he is in danger I do not see.
Cucumber is bitter.
Throw it away.
There are briars in the road.
Turn aside from them.
This is enough.
Do not add, and why were such things made in the world?
For thou wilt be ridiculed by a man who is acquainted with nature,
as thou wouldst be ridiculed by a carpenter and shoemaker,
if thou didst find fault because thou seest in their workshop.
Shavings and cuttings from the things which they make.
You need to add some text for me to talk,
and yet they have places into which
they can throw these shavings and cuttings,
and the universal nature has no external space.
But the wondrous part of her art is that though she has circumscribed herself,
everything within her which appears to decay and to grow old and to be useless,
she changes into herself and again makes other new things from.
These vary same, so that she requires neither substance from without,
nor wants a place into which she may cast not which decays.
She is content then with her own space and her own matter and her own art.
Suppose that men kill thee, cut thee in pieces, curse thee.
What then can these things do to prevent thy mind from remaining pure,
wise, sober, just?
For instance, if a man should stand by a limpid pure spring and curse it,
the spring never ceases sending up potable water,
and if he should cast clay into it or filth, it will speedily disperse them
and wash them out and will not be at all polluted.
How then shalt thou possess a perpetual fountain and not a mere well?
By forming thyself hourly to freedom, conjoined with contentment, simplicity,
and modesty, he who does not know what the world is,
does not know where he is, and he who does not know for what purpose the world exists,
does not know who he is, nor what the world is.
But he who has failed in any one of these things could not even say for what purpose he
exists himself. What then dost thou think of him who avoids or seeks the praise of those
who applaud, of men who know not either where they are or who they are?
Dost thou wish to be praised by a man who curses himself thrice every hour?
Whatst thou wish to please a man who does not please himself?
Does a man please himself who repents of nearly everything that he does?
No longer let thy breathing, only act in concert with the air which surrounds thee,
but let thy intelligence also now be in harmony with the nine intelligence
which embraces all things, for the intelligent power is no less diffused in all parts
and pervades all things for him who is willing to draw it to him
than the aerial power for him who is able to respire it.
Generally wickedness does no harm at all to the universe,
and particularly the wickedness of one man does no harm to another.
It is only harmful to him who has it in his power to be released from it
as soon as he shall choose. To my own free will,
the free will of my neighbor is just as indifferent as his poor breath and flesh.
For though we are made especially for the sake of one another,
still the ruling power of each of us has its own office.
The sun appears to be poured down, and in all directions indeed it is diffused,
yet it is not effused. For this diffusion is extension.
Accordingly its rays are called extensions because they are extended.
You need to add some text for me to talk.
But one may judge what kind of a thing a ray is if he looks at the sun's light
passing through a narrow opening into a darkened room, for it is extended in a right line,
and as it were is divided when it meets with any solid body
which stands in the way and intercepts the air beyond.
But there, the light remains fixed. Such, then, ought to be the outpouring
and diffusion of the understanding, and it should in no way be an effusion,
but an extension, and it should make no violent or impetuous collision
with the obstacles which are in its way nor yet fall down,
but be fixed, and enlighten that which receives it.
For a body will deprive itself of the illumination if it does not admit it.
Ye who fears death either fears the loss of sensation, or a different kind of sensation,
or a different kind of sensation. But if thou shalt have no sensation,
neither wilt thou feel any harm, and if thou shalt acquire another kind of sensation,
thou wilt be a different kind of living being, and thou wilt.
Men exist for the sake of one another. Teach them, then, or bear with them.
In one way an arrow moves, in another way the mind.
The mind indeed, both when it exercises caution, and when it is employed about inquiry,
moves straight onward, not the less, and to its object.
Enter into every man's ruling faculty, and also let every other man enter into thine.
Book 9. He who acts unjustly acts impiously.
For since the universal nature has made rational animals, for the sake of one another,
to help one another according to their deserts, but in no way to injure one another,
he who transgresses her will, and he too who lies is guilty of impiety to the same divinity.
For the universal nature is the nature of things that are,
and things that are, have a relation to all things that come into existence.
And further, you need to add some text for me to talk.
He then who lies intentionally is guilty of impiety inasmuch as he acts unjustly by deceiving.
To truth, for he had received powers from nature through the neglect of which he is not
able now to distinguish falsehood from truth. And indeed, he who pursues pleasure as good,
and avoids pain as evil, is guilty of impiety. For of necessity such a man must often find
fault with the universal nature, alleging that it assigns things to the bad and the good,
contrary to their deserts, because frequently the bad are in the enjoyment of pleasure,
and possess the things which procure. Pleasure, but the good have pain for their share,
and the things which cause pain. And further, he who is afraid of pain will sometimes also be
afraid of some of the things which will happen in the world, and even this is impiety.
And he who pursues pleasure will not abstain from injustice, and this is plainly impiety.
Now with respect to the things towards which the universal nature is equally affected,
for it would not have made both, unless it was equally affected towards both.
Towards these they who wish to follow nature should be of the same mind with it and equally
affected. You need to add some text for me to talk. And I say that the universal nature
employs them equally, instead of saying that they happen alike to those who are produced
in continuous series, and to those who come after them by virtue of a certain original
movement of providence, according to which it moved from a certain beginning to this ordering
of things, principles of the things which were to be, and having determined powers productive
of beings and of changes and of such like successions. With respect to pain then,
and pleasure, or death and life, or honour and dishonour, which the universal nature
employs equally, whoever is not equally affected is manifestly acting impiously.
It would be a man's happiest lot to depart from mankind without having had any taste of lying
and hypocrisy and luxury and pride. However to breathe out one's life when a man has had enough
of these things, is the next best voyage, as the saying is.
Has the saying is, I asked, the saying is, the saying is, yet induced thee to fly from
this pestilence. For the destruction of the understanding is a pestilence, much more indeed
than any such corruption and change of this atmosphere which surrounds us.
For this corruption is a pestilence of animals, so far as they are animals. Do not despise death,
but be well content with it, since this too is one of those things which nature wills.
For such as it is to be young and to grow old, and to increase and to reach maturity,
and to have teeth and beard and grey hairs, and to beget and to be pregnant and to bring forth
and all the other natural operations which the seasons of.
This, then, is consistent with the character of a reflecting man, to be neither careless nor
impatient nor contemptuous with respect to death, but to wait for it. As thou now waitest
for the time when the child shall come out of thy wise womb, so be ready for the time
when thy soul shall fall out of this. But if thou requires also a vulgar kind of comfort
which shall reach thy heart, thou wilt be made best reconciled to death by observing
the objects from which thou art going to be removed, and the morals of those with whom
thy soul will no longer be mingled. For it is no way right to be offended with men,
but it is thy duty to care for them and to bear with them gently, and yet to remember that thy
departure will be not from men who have the same principles as thyself. For this is the
only thing, if there be any, which could draw us the contrary way and attach us to life,
to be permitted to live with those who have the same principles as ourselves.
But now thou seest how great is the trouble arising from the discordance of those who
live together, so that thou mayest say, Come quick, O death, lest perchance I,
in A who does wrong does wrong against himself, he who acts unjustly acts unjustly to himself
because he makes himself bad. He often acts unjustly who does not do a certain thing,
not only he who does a certain thing, thy present opinion founded on understanding,
and thy present conduct directed to social good, and thy present disposition of contentment
with everything which happens, that is enough. Check desire. Extinguish appetite.
Keep the ruling faculty in its own power. You need to add some text for me to talk,
among the animals which have not reason. One life is distributed, but among reasonable
animals one intelligent soul is distributed. Just as there is one earth of all things which
are of an earthy nature, and we see by one light and breathe one air, all things which
participate in anything which is common to them all move towards that which is of the same kind
with themselves. Everything which is earthy turns towards the earth. Everything which is liquid
flows together, and everything which is of an aerial kind does the same so that they require
something to keep them asunder, and the fire indeed moves upwards on account of the elemental
fire, but it is so ready to be kindled together with all the fire which is here
that even every substance which is somewhat dry is easily ignited because there is less mingled
with it, of that which is a hindrance to ignition. Accordingly then, everything also
which participates in the common intelligent nature moves in like manner towards that which
is of the same kind with itself, or moves even more. For so much, as it is superior
in comparison with all other end things, in the same degree also is it more ready to mingle
and to be fused with that which is akin to it. You need to add some text for me to talk.
Accordingly among animals, devoid of reason, we find swarms of bees, and herds of cattle,
and the nurture of young birds, and in a manner loves, for even in animals there are souls,
and that power which brings them together is seen to exert itself in the superior degree,
and in such a way as never has been observed in plants, nor in stones,
but in rational animals there are political communities, and friendships,
and families, and meetings of people. Thus the ascent to the higher degree is able to produce
a sympathy even in things which are separated, but still though men strive to avoid this union,
they are caught and held by it, for their nature is too strong for them,
and thou wilt see what I say if thou only observest.
Sooner then will one find anything earthy which comes in contact with no earthy thing
than a man altogether separated from other men. Both man and God, and the universe,
produce fruit. At the proper seasons each produces it. But if usage has especially
fixed these terms to the vine and like things, this is nothing. Reason produces
fruit both for all and for itself, and there are produced from it other things of the same kind
as reason itself, if thou art able, correct by teaching those who do wrong. But if thou
canst not, remember that indulgence is given to thee for this purpose. And the gods, too,
are indulgent to such persons, and for some purposes they even help them to get health,
wealth, reputation. So kind they are, and it is in nenthy power also, or say, who hinders thee.
Today I have got out of all trouble, or rather I have cast out all trouble, for it was not
outside, but within, and in my opinions. All things are the same, familiar in experience,
and ephemeral in time, and worthless in the matter. Everything now is just as it was in
the time of those whom we have buried. Things stand outside of us, themselves, by themselves,
neither knowing aught of themselves, nor expressing any judgment.
The ruling faculty. Not in passivity, but in activity, lie the evil and the good of the
social animal, just as his virtue and his vice lie not in passivity, but in activity.
Penetrate inwards, into men's leading principles, and thou wilt see what judges
thou art afraid of, and what kind of judges they are of themselves. It is thy duty to leave
another man's wrongful act there where it is, on termination of activity, cessation from
movement and opinion, and, in a sense, their death is no evil. Turn thy thoughts now to
the consideration of thy life, thy life as a child, as a youth, thy manhood, thy old age,
for in these also every change was a death. Is this anything to fear? Turn thy thoughts now
to thy life under thy grandfather, then to thy life under thy mother, then to thy life
under thy father. You need to add some text for me to talk. Hasten to examine thy own
ruling faculty, and that of the universe, and that of thy neighbor, thy own, that thou
mayest make it just. In like manner, then, neither are the termination and cessation and
change of thy whole life a thing to be afraid of. As thou thyself art a component,
part of a social system, so let every act of thine be a component part of social life.
Whatever act of thine, then, has no reference either immediately or remotely to a social end.
This tears asunder thy life, and does not allow it to be one, and it is of the nature
of a mutiny. Just as when in a popular assembly a man acting by himself stands
apart from the general agreement, quarrels of little children, and their sports,
and poor spirits, carrying about dead bodies, such as everything. And so what is exhibited
in the representation of the mansions of the dead strikes our eyes more clearly.
Examine into the quality of the form of an object, nand, detach it altogether from its
material part, and then contemplate it, then determine the time, the longest, which a thing
of this peculiar form is naturally made to endure. Thou hast endured infinite troubles
through not being contented with thy ruling faculty, when it does the things which it is
constituted by nature to do. But enough of this. When another blames thee or hates thee,
or when men say about thee anything injurious, approach their poor souls,
penetrate within, and see what kind of men they are, thou wilt discover that there is
no reason to take any trouble, that these men may have this or that opinion about thee.
However thou must be well disposed towards them, for by nature they are friends,
and the gods too aid them in all ways, by dreams, by signs, towards the attainment of
those things on which they set a value. You need to add some text for me to talk.
And either the universal intelligence puts itself in motion for every separate effect,
and if this is so, be thou content with that which is the result of its activity,
or it puts itself in motion once, and everything else comes by way of sequence in a manner.
In a word, if there is a god, all is well, and if chance rules, do not thou also be
governed by it. Soon will the earth cover us all, then the earth too will change,
and the things also which result from change will continue to change forever.
For if a man reflects on the changes and transformations which follow one another,
like wave after wave, and their rapidity, he will despise everything which is perishable.
But how worthless are all these poor people who are engaged in matters political,
and, as they suppose, are playing the philosopher, all drivelers! Well then,
man, do what nature now requires. Set thyself in motion, if it is in thy power,
and do not look about thee to see if any one will observe it, nor yet expect Plato's Republic,
but be content, if the smallest thing goes on well, and consider such an event to be
no small matter, for who can change men's opinions? And without a change of opinions,
what else is there than the slavery of men who groan while they pretend to obey?
They themselves shall judge whether they discovered what the common nature required,
and trained themselves accordingly. But if they acted like tragedy heroes,
no one has condemned me to imitate them. Simple and modest is the work of philosophy.
Draw me not aside to indolence and pride. Look down from above on the countless herds of men
and their countless solemnities, and the infinitely varied voyagings in storms and calms,
and the differences among those who are born, who live together and die. You need to add some
text for me to talk. And consider, too, the life lived by others in olden time, and the life of
those who will live after thee, and the life now lived among barbarous nations, and how many
know not even thy name, and how many will soon forget it, and how they who perhaps now are
praising thee will very soon blame thee, and that neither apostumous name is of any.
Let there be freedom from perturbations with respect to the things which come from the
external cause. Let there be justice, destrest, my end, birth to dissolution,
and the illimitable time before birth, as well as the equally boundless time after dissolution.
All that thou seest will quickly perish, and those who have been spectators of its dissolution
will very soon perish, too. And he who dies at the extremist old age will be brought into
the same condition with him who died prematurely. What are these men's leading principles,
and about what kind of things are they busy, and for what kind of reasons do they love
and honor? Imagine that thou seest their poor souls laid bare. When they think that
they do harm by their blame, or good by their praise, what an idea! Loss is nothing else
than change. But the universal nature delights in change. And, in obedience to her, all things
are now done well, and from eternity have been done in like form, and will be such to time
without end. What then dost thou say? That all things have been, and all things always will be
bad, and that no power has ever been found in so many gods to rectify these things. But the
world has been condemned to be found in never ceasing evil. The rottenness of the matter,
which is the foundation of everything, water, dust, bones, filth, or again marble rocks,
the colossities of the earth, and gold and silver, the sediments and garments, only bits of hair,
and that which is of the nature of end-breath. What unsettles thee? Is it the form of the
thing? Look at it. Or is it the matter? Look at it. But besides these there is nothing.
Towards the gods, then, now become at last more simple and better. It is the same whether we
examine these things for a hundred years or three. If any man has done wrong, the harm is his own.
But perhaps he has not done wrong. Either all things proceed from one intelligence source
and come together as in one body, and the part ought not to find fault with what is
done for the benefit of the whole, or there are only atoms and nothing else than mixture
and dispersion. Why, then, art thou disturbed? Say to the ruling faculty. Art thou dead?
Art thou corrupted? Art thou plain a hypocrite? Art thou become a beast? Dost thou herd and
feed with the rest? If, then, they have no power, why dost thou pray to them? But if
they have power, why dost thou not pray for them to give thee the faculty of not fearing
any of the things which thou fearest, or of not desiring any of the things which thou
desirest, or not being pained at anything, rather than pray that any of these things
should not happen? Or, for certainly, if they can cooperate with men, they can cooperate
for these purposes. But perhaps thou wilt say, The gods have placed them in thy power.
Well, then, is it not better to use what is in thy power like a free man,
than to desire in a slavish and abject way? What is not in thy power, and who has told
thee that the gods do not aid us even in the things in which are in our power?
Do thou pray thus, How shall I not desire to lie with her?
Another prays thus, How shall I be released from this?
Another prays, How shall I not desire to be released?
Another thus, How shall I not lose my little son?
Thou thus, How shall I not be afraid to lose him?
You need to add some text for me to talk. Epicurus says,
In my sickness my conversation was not about my bodily sufferings,
nor, says he, did I talk on such subjects to those who visited me.
But I continue to discourse on the nature of things as before.
Keeping to this main point, Infine, turn thy prayers this way, and see what comes.
You need to add some text for me to talk.
Do, then, the same that he did both in sickness.
If thou art sick, and in any other circumstances, for never to desert philosophy
in any events that may befall us, nor to hold trifling talk either with an ignorant man,
or with one unacquainted with nature, is a principle of all schools of philosophy.
But to be intent only on that which thou art now,
doing, and on, the instrument by which thou doest it.
When thou art offended with any man's shameless conduct, immediately ask thyself,
Is it possible, then, that shameless men should not be in the world?
For this man also is one of those shameless men who must of necessity be in the world.
Let the same considerations be present to thy mind in the case of the knave,
and the faithless man, and of every man who does wrong in any way.
For at the same time that thou dost remind thyself that it is impossible
that such kind of men should not exist, thou wilt become more kindly disposed
towards every one individually.
It is useful to perceive this, too, immediately when the occasion arises,
what virtue nature has given to man to oppose to every wrongful act.
For she has given to man, as an antidote against the stupid man,
mildness, and against another kind of man, some other power.
And in all cases it is possible for thee to correct,
by teaching the man who is gone astray.
For every man who errs misses his object, and is gone astray.
Besides, wherein hast thou been injured?
For thou wilt find that no one among those against whom thou art irritated
has done anything by which thy mind could be made worse.
But that which is evil to thee, and harmful, has its foundation only in the mind.
And what harm is done, or what is there?
Strange, if the man who has not been instructed does the acts of an uninstructed man.
Consider, whether thou shouldst not rather blame thyself,
because thou didst not expect such a man to err in such a way.
For thou hast means, given thee by thy reason,
to suppose that it was likely that he would commit this error,
and yet thou hast forgotten, and art amazed that he has erred.
But most of all, when thou blamest a man as faithless or ungrateful,
turn to thyself, for the fault is manifestly thy own.
Whether thou didst trust that a man who had such a disposition would keep his promise.
Or when conferring thy kindness, thou didst not confer it absolutely,
nor yet in such way as to have received from thy very act all the profit.
For what more dost thou want when thou hast done a man a service?
Art thou not content that thou hast done something conformable to thy nature,
and dost thou seek to be paid for it?
You need to add some text for me to talk.
For as these members are formed for a particular purpose,
and by working according to their several constitutions, obtain what is their own.
Wilt thou then, my soul, never be good and simple, and one and naked,
more manifest than the body which surrounds thee?
Wilt thou never enjoy an affectionate and contented disposition?
Wilt thou never be full, and without a want of any kind,
longing for nothing more, nor desiring anything, either animate or inanimate,
for the enjoyment of? You need to add some text for me to talk.
But wilt thou be satisfied with thy present condition,
and pleased with all that is about thee?
And wilt thou convince thyself that thou hast everything, and that it comes from the gods?
That everything is well for thee, and will be well whatever shall please them,
good and just and beautiful?
Which generates and holds together all things, and contains and embraces all things,
which are dissolved for the production of other like things?
Nor yet desiring time, wherein thou shalt have longer enjoyment,
or place, or pleasant climate, or society of men with whom thou mayest live in harmony.
Wilt thou never be such that thou shalt so dwell in community with gods and men,
as neither to find fault with them at all, nor to be condemned by them?
Observe what thy nature requires, so far as thou art governed by nature only.
And all this thou mayest allow thyself, if thy nature,
so far as thou art a rational animal, shall not be made worse by it.
And but the rational animal is consequently also a political, social animal.
Use these rules then, and trouble thyself about nothing else.
Everything which happens, either happens in such wise as thou art formed by nature to bear it,
or as thou art not formed by nature to bear it.
But if it happens in such wise as thou art not formed by nature to bear it,
do not complain, for it will perish after it has consumed thee.
Remember, however, that thou art formed by nature to bear everything,
with respect to which it depends on thy own opinion to make it endurable and tolerable.
By thinking that it is either thy interest or thy think, if a man is mistaken,
instruct him kindly, and show him his error.
But if thou art not able, blame thyself, or blame not even thyself.
Whatever may happen to thee, it was prepared for thee from all eternity,
and the implication of causes was from eternity spinning the thread of thy being,
and of that which is incident to it.
Whether the universe is a concourse of atoms, or nature is a system,
let this first be established, that I am a part of the whole which is governed by nature.
For remembering this, inasmuch as I am a part, I shall be discontented with none of the things
which are assigned to me out of the whole, for nothing is injurious to the part,
if it is for the advantage of the whole, for the whole contains nothing which is not
for its advantage, and all natures indeed have this common principle,
but the nature of the universe has this principle.
Besides, that it cannot be incompelled even by any external cause to generate anything harmful
to itself. By remembering then, that I am a part of such a whole, I shall be content with
everything that happens, and inasmuch as I am in a manner intimately related to the parts
which are of the same kind with myself, I shall do nothing unsocial, but I shall rather direct
myself to the things which are of the same kind with myself, and I shall turn all my efforts
to the common interest, and divert them from the contrary. Now, if these things are done so,
life must flow on happily, just as thou mayst observe that the life of a citizen is happy,
who continues a course of action which is advantageous to his fellow citizens,
and is content with whatever the state may assign to him.
The parts of the whole everything, I mean, which is naturally comprehended in the universe,
must of necessity perish. But let this be understood in this sense, that they must
undergo change, but if this is naturally both an evil and a necessity for the parts,
the whole would not continue to exist in a good condition, the parts being subject to change and
constituted so as to perish in various ways. For whether did Nature herself design to do evil
to the things which are parts of herself, and to make them subject to evil and of necessity
fall into evil, or have such results happened without her knowing it? You need to add some
text for me to talk. But if a man should even drop the term Nature as an efficient power,
and should speak of these things as natural, even then it would be ridiculous to affirm at
the same time that the parts of the whole are in their nature subject to change,
and at the same time to be surprised or vexed as if something were happening
contrary to Nature, particularly as the dissolution of things is in to those things
of which each thing is composed, both these suppositions indeed are incredible. For there
is either a dispersion of the elements out of which everything has been compounded,
or a change from the solid to and the earthy and from the airy to the aerial,
so that these parts are taken back into the universal reason, whether this at certain periods
is consumed by fire or renewed by. And do not imagine that the solid and the airy part
belong to thee from the time of generation. This, then, which has received the accretion,
changes, not that which thy mother brought forth. But suppose that this which thy mother
brought forth implicates thee very much with that other part, which has the peculiar quality
of change. This is nothing, in fact, in the way of objection to what is said. When thou hast
assumed these names, good, modest, true, rational, a man of equanimity and magnanimous,
take care that thou dost not change these names, and if thou shouldst lose them.
And remember that the term rational was intended to signify a discriminating attention
to every several thing, and freedom from negligence of the things which are assigned
to thee by the common nature, and that magnanimity is the elevation of the intelligent
part above the pleasurable or painful sensations of the flesh, and above that poor thing called
fame, and death, and all such things. For to continue to be such as thou hast his or two
been, and to be Tom in pieces and defiled in such a life, is the character of a very stupid
man, and one over fond of his life. And like those half devoured fighters with wild beasts,
who though covered with wounds and gore, still entreat to be kept to the following day,
though they will be exposed. If then thou maintainest thyself in the possession of
these names, without desiring to be called by these names by others, thou wilt be another
person and wilt enter on another life. Therefore, fix thyself in the possession of
these few names, and if thou art able to abide in them, abide as if thou wast removed
to certain islands of the happy out of them, and dost not maintain thy hold, go courageously
into some nook where thou shalt maintain them, or even depart at once from life,
not in passion, but with simplicity and freedom and modesty, after doing this one
laudable thing, at least in thy life, to have gone out of it thus.
You need to add some text for me to talk. In order, however, to the remembrance of these names,
it will greatly help thee, if thou rememberest the gods, and that they wish not to be
flattered, but wish all reasonable beings to be made like themselves. Does the work of a
bee is a bee, and that, what does the work of a man, is a man? Mime, war, astonishment,
torpor, slavery, will daily wipe out those holy principles of thine, but it is thy duty,
so to look on and so to do everything, that at the same time the power of dealing with
circumstances is perfected, and the contemplative faculty is exercised, and the confidence which
comes from the knowledge of each several thing is maintained without showing it,
but yet not concealed. You need to add some text for me to talk.
For when wilt thou enjoy simplicity, when gravity, and when the knowledge of every
several thing, both what it is in substance, and what place it has in the universe,
and how long it is formed to exist, and of what things it is compounded,
and to whom it can belong, and who are able both to give it, and take it away.
A spider is proud when it has caught a fly, and another when he has caught a poor hair,
and another when he has taken a little fish in a net, and another when he has taken wild
boars, and another when he has taken bears. Are not these robbers, if thou examinest
their opinions? Acquire the contemplative way of seeing how all things change into one another,
and constantly attend to it, and exercise thyself about this part of philosophy,
for nothing is so much adapted to produce magnanimity. Such a man has put off the
body, and as he sees that he must, no one knows how soon go away from among men,
and leave everything here. He gives himself up entirely to just doing in all his actions,
and in everything else that happens he resigns himself to the universal nature.
But as to what any man shall say, or think about him, or do against him,
he never even thinks of it being himself contented with these two things, with acting
justly in what he now does, and being satisfied with what is now assigned to him,
and he lays aside all distracting and busy pursuits, and desires nothing else than to
accomplish the straight course through the law, and by accomplishing the straight course to
follow God. What need is there of suspicious fear, since it is in thy power to inquire
what ought to be done? And if thou seest clear, go by this way content, without turning back.
But if any other things oppose thee, go on according to thy powers with due consideration,
keeping to that which appears to be just. For it is best to reach this object,
and if thou dost fail, let thy failure be in attempting this.
He who follows reason in all things, is both tranquil and active at the same time.
Now hast not forgotten, I suppose, that those who assume arrogant heirs in bestowing their praise
or blame on others, are such as they are at bed, and at board, and now hast not forgotten
what they do, and what they avoid, and what they pursue, and how they steal, and how they
rob, not with hands and feet, but with their most valuable part, means of which there is
When a man chooses, fidelity, modesty, truth, law, a good demon, happiness, it will make no
difference. To her who gives and takes back all, to nature, the man who is instructed and
modest says, Give what thou wilt, take back what thou wilt. Short is the little which remains
to thee of life. Live as on a mountain. For it makes no difference whether a man lives there
or here, if he lives everywhere in the world, as in a state, political community.
Let men see. Let them know a real man, who lives according to nature.
Constantly contemplate the whole of time and the whole of substance,
and consider that all individual things as to substance are a grain of a fig,
and as to time the turning of a gimlet. Look at everything that exists, and observe that it
is already in dissolution and in change, and as it were putrefaction or dispersion,
or that everything is so. Consider what men are when they are eating, sleeping,
generating, easing themselves, and so forth. Then what kind of men they are when they are
imperious and arrogant, or angry and scolding from their elevated place, but a short time
ago, to how many they were slaves, and for what things, and after a little time consider
what a condition they will be. And it is for its good, at the time when nature brings it.
And is not this too said, that this or that loves, is want to be produced?
Either thou livest here, and hast already accustomed thyself to it,
or thou art going away, and this was thy own will, or thou art dying, and hast
discharged thy duty. But besides these things, there is nothing. Be of good cheer then.
Let this always be plain to thee, that this piece of land is like any other,
and that all things here are the same, with things on top of a mountain,
or on the seashore, or wherever thou choosest to be. For thou wilt find just what Plato says,
dwelling within the walls of a city, as in a shepherd's fold on a mountain.
What is my ruling faculty now to me, and of what nature am I now making it?
Is it void of understanding? Is it loosed and rent asunder from social life?
Is it melted into and mixed with the poor flesh so as to move together with it?
He who flies from his master is a runaway, but the law is master,
and he who breaks the law is a runaway. And he also who is grieved or angry or afraid
is dissatisfied because something has been or nis or shall be of the things which are appointed
by him who rules all things, and he is law, and assigns to every man what is fit. He then who
fears or is grieved or is angry is a runaway. A man deposits seed in a womb and goes away,
and then another cause takes it and labors on it and makes a child. Again the child passes
food down through the throat, and then another cause takes it and makes perception and motion,
and in fine life and strength and other things, how many and how strange. Observe then the things
which are produced in such a hidden way, and see the power just as we see the power which
carries things downwards and upwards, not. Constantly consider how all things such as they
now are, in time past also were, and consider that they will be the same again.
And place before thy eyes entire dramas and stages of the same form whatever thou hast learned
from thy experience or from older history, for example, the whole court of Hadrian,
and the whole court of Antoninus, and the whole court of Philip, Alexander,
Croesus, for all those were such dramas as we see now only with different actors.
Imagine every man who is grieved at anything or discontented to be like a pig which is
sacrificed and kicks and screams. Like this pig also is he who on his bed in silence laments
the bonds in which we are held, and consider that only to the rational animal is it given to.
Follow voluntarily what happens, but simply to follow is a necessity imposed on all.
Severally, on the occasion of every thing that thou doest, pause and ask thyself,
if death is a dreadful thing because it deprives thee of this.
When thou art offended at any man's fault, forthwith turn to thyself, and reflect in
what like manner thou dost err. Thyself, for example, in thinking that money is a good thing,
or pleasure, or a bit of reputation, and the like. For by attending to this,
thou wilt quickly forget thy anger. If this consideration also is added, that the man is
compelled, for what else could he do? Or, if thou art able, take away from him the compulsion.
You need to add some text for me to talk. When thou hast seen Satyron the Socratic,
think of either Eudicius or Hymen, and when thou hast seen Euphrates, think of Eutychian
or Silvanus, and when thou hast seen Alcefron, think of Tropeiophorus, and when thou hast seen
Xenophon, think of Credo or Severus, and when thou hast looked on thyself,
think of any other Caesar, and in the case of, then let this thought be in thy mind,
where then are those men? Nowhere, or nobody knows where. For thus continuously,
thou wilt look at human things as smoke, and nothing at all, especially if thou reflectest
at the same time, that what has once changed will never exist again, in the infinite duration of
time. But thou, in what a brief space of time is thy existence, and why art thou not content
to pass through this short time in an orderly way? What matter and opportunity for thy activity
art thou avoiding? For what else are all these things, except exercises for the reason,
when it has viewed carefully, and by examination into their nature, the things which happen in
life? Persevere then, until thou shalt have made these things thy own, as the stomach which
is strengthened makes all things its own, as the blazing fire makes flame and brightness out
of. Let it not be in any man's power to say truly of thee, that thou art not simple,
or that thou art not good. But let him be a liar, for who is he that shall hinder thee
from being good and simple? Do thou only determine to live no longer, unless thou
shalt be such? For neither does reason allow thee to live, if thou art not such.
What is that which, as to this material, our life, can be done or said in the way most
conformable to reason? You need to add some text for me to talk. Thou wilt not cease
to lament till thy mind is in such a condition that, what luxury is to those who enjoy
pleasure, such shall be to thee, in the matter which is subjected and presented to thee.
For whatever this may be, it is in thy power to do it or to say it,
and do not make excuses that thou art hindered. And it is in his power everywhere.
Now it is not given to a cylinder to move everywhere by its own motion,
nor yet to water, nor to fire, nor to anything else which is governed by nature,
or an irrational soul, for the things which, but intelligence and reason, are able to go
through everything that opposes them, and in such manner as they are formed by nature,
and as they choose. Place before thy eyes this facility with which the reason will be carried
through all things, as fire upwards, as a stone downwards, as a cylinder down an inclined
surface. And seek for nothing, for all other obstacles either affect the body only which is
a dead thing, or, except through opinion and the yielding of the reason itself,
they do not crush nor do any harm of any kind, for if they did, he who felt it would
immediately become bad. Now, in the case of all things which have a certain constitution,
whatever harm may happen to any of them, that which is so affected becomes consequently worse.
But in the like case a man becomes both better, if one may say so, and more worthy of praise and
be making a right use of these accidents. And finally remember that nothing harms him who
is really a citizen, which does not harm the state, nor yet does anything harm the state,
which does not harm law, order, and of these things which are called misfortunes,
not one harms law, what then does not harm, for example, leaves, some the wind scatters on
the ground, so is the race of men, leaves also are thy children, and leaves too are they who
cry out as if they were worthy of credit and bestow their praise, or on the contrary curse,
or secretly blame and sneer, for all such things as these are produced in the season of spring,
as the poet says, then the wind casts them down, then the forest produces other leaves
in their places. A little time and thou shalt close thy eyes, and him who has attended thee
to thy grave another soon will lament, and the healthy hearing and smelling ought to be
ready to perceive all that can be heard and smelled, and accordingly the healthy
understanding ought to be prepared for everything which happens. There is no man so fortunate that
there shall not be by him when he is dying, some who are pleased with what is going to happen.
Pose that he was a good and wise man. Will there not be at last someone to say to himself,
Let us at last breathe freely, being relieved from this schoolmaster. It is true that he was
harsh to none of us, but I perceived that he tacitly condemns us. Thou wilt consider this
then, when thou art dying, and thou wilt depart more contentedly by reflecting thus.
I am going away from such a life, in which even my associates in behalf of whom I have
so much, prayed and cared. Do not, however, for this reason go away less kindly disposed to them,
but preserving thy own character, and friendly and benevolent and mild, and on the other hand,
not as if thou wast torn away, but as when a man dies. A quiet death, the poor soul is
easily separated from the body. Such also ought thy departure from men to be. Why then
should a man cling to a longer stay here? But does she now dissolve the union?
Well, I am separated as from kinsmen, not, however, drag resisting, but without compulsion.
For this, too, is one of the things according to nature. Accustom thyself as much as possible
on the occasion of anything being done by any person to inquire with thyself. For what object
is this man doing this? Remember that this which pulls the strings is the thing which
is hidden within. This is the power of end persuasion. This is life. This, if one may so
say, is man. In contemplating thyself, never include the vessel which surrounds thee,
and these instruments which are attached about it. For they are like to an axe,
differing only in this, that they grow to the body. Book 11. These are the properties
of the rational soul. It sees itself, analyses itself, and makes itself such as it chooses,
the fruit which it bears itself enjoys, for the fruits of plants, and that in animals
which corresponds to fruits others enjoy. It obtains its own end, wherever the limit of
it is fixed, not as in a dance, and in a play, and in such like things, where the whole action
is incomplete, if anything cuts it short. But in every part, and wherever it may be stopped,
it makes what has been set before it full and complete, so that it can say, I have what is
my own, you need to add some text for me to talk. And further, it traverses the whole
universe, and the surrounding vacuum, and surveys its form, and it extends itself into
the infinity of time, and embraces and comprehends the periodical renovation of all things,
and it comprehends that those who come after us will see nothing new,
nor have those before us seen anything more. Who, his forty years old, if he has any
understanding at all, has seen by virtue of the uniformity that prevails all things which have
been, and all that will be, this too, is a property of the rational soul, love of one's
neighbor, and truth and modesty, and to value nothing more than itself, which is also the
property of law. Thus then, right reason differs not at all from the reason of justice.
Thou wilt set little value on pleasing song, and dancing, and the pancratium,
if thou wilt distribute the melody of the voice into its several sounds,
and ask thyself as to each, if thou art mastered by this, for thou wilt be
prevented by shame from confessing it, and in the matter of dancing,
if at each movement and attitude, thou wilt do thee. Same, and the like also,
in the matter of the pancratium. In all things then, except virtue, and the acts of virtue,
remember to apply thyself to their several parts, and by this division,
to come to value them little, and apply this rule, also, to thy whole life.
You need to add some text for me to talk. What a soul that is, which is ready, if at any
moment it must be separated from the body, and ready either to be extinguished or dispersed,
or continue to exist, but so that this readiness comes from a man's own judgment,
not from mere obstinacy, as with the Christians, but considerately and with dignity,
and in a way to persuade another, without. And how is this accomplished well, except by
general principles, some about the nature of the universe, and others about the proper
constitution of man? At first tragedies were brought on the stage as means of reminding men
of the things which happen to them, and that it is according to nature for things to happen so,
and that, if you are delighted. With what is shown on the stage, you should not be
troubled with that which takes place on the larger stage. Have I done something for the
general interest? Well then, I have had my reward. Let this always be present to thy mind,
and never stop doing such good. What is thy art? And, indeed, some things are said well
by the dramatic writers, of which kind is the following, E. Tau and me and my children.
If the gods neglect, this has its reason too, and life's harvest,
reap like the wheat's fruitful ear, and other things of the same kind.
After tragedy the old comedy was introduced, which had a magisterial freedom of speech,
and by its very plainness of speaking was useful in reminding men to beware of
insolence. And for this purpose too, diogenies used to take from these writers.
But as to the middle comedy which came next, observe what it was, and again,
for what object the new comedy was introduced, which gradually sunk down into a mere mimic
artifice. That some good things are said even by these writers everybody knows.
But the whole plan of such poetry and dramaturgy, to what end does it look?
That there is not another condition of life so well suited for philosophizing as this
in which thou now happenest to be. A branch cut off from the adjacent branch
must of necessity be cut off from the whole tree also. So too a man,
when he is separated from another man, has fallen off from the whole social community.
Now as to a branch, another cuts it off, but a man by his own act separates himself
from his neighbor when he hates him, and turns away from him, and he does not know
that he has at the same time cut himself off from the whole social system. Yet he has his
privilege certainly from Zeus, who frames society. For it is in our power to grow again
to that which is near to us, and be to come, a part which helps to make up the whole.
However, if it often happens, this kind nough separation, it makes it difficult for that
which detaches itself to be brought to unity, and to be restored to its. You need to add
some text for me to talk. Finally the branch, which from the first grew together
with the tree, and has continued to have one life with it, is not like that which after
being cut off, is then ingrafted. For this is something like what the gardeners mean
when they say that it grows with the rest of the tree, but that it has not the same mind
with it. You need to add some text for me to talk. As those who try to stand in thy way when
thou are proceeding according to right reason, will not be able to turn thee aside from thy
proper action, so neither let them drive thee from thy benevolent feelings towards them,
but be on thy guard equally in both matters, not only in the matter of steady judgment and action,
gentleness towards those who try to hinder or otherwise trouble thee. For this also is a
weakness, to be vexed at them, as well as to be diverted from thy course of action,
and to give way through fear, for both are equally deserters from their post, the man
who does it through fear, and the man who is alienated from him who is by nature a kinsman
and a friend. There is no nature which is inferior to art, for the arts imitate the nature
of things. Now all arts do the inferior things for the sake of the superior, therefore the
universal nature does so too, and indeed hence. If the things do not come to thee,
the pursuits and avoidances of which disturb thee, still in a manner thou goest to them,
let then thy judgment about them be at rest, and they will remain quiet,
and thou wilt not be seen either pursuing or avoiding. The spherical form of the soul
maintains its figure, when it is neither extended towards any object, nor contracted
inwards, nor dispersed, nor sinks down, but is illuminated by light, by which it sees the
truth, the truth of all things, and the truth that is in itself. Suppose any man shall
despise me, let him look to that himself, but I will look to this, that I be not
discovered doing or saying anything deserving of contempt, shall any man hate me, but I
will be mild and benevolent towards every man, and ready to show even him his mistake,
not reproachfully, nor yet is making a display of my endurance, but nobly and honestly,
like the great Phocion, unless indeed he only assumed it. For the interior parts
ought to be such, and a man ought to be seen by the gods neither dissatisfied with anything
nor complaining. For what evil is it to thee, if thou art now doing what is agreeable to thy
nature, and art satisfied with that which at this moment is suitable to the nature of the
universe, since thou art a human being placed? At thy post, in order that what is for the
common advantage may be done in some way, men despise one another, and flatter one another,
and men wish to raise themselves above one another, and crouch before one another.
What art thou doing, man? There is no occasion to give this notice. It will soon show itself
by acts. Such as a man's character is, he immediately shows it in his eyes, just as he
who is beloved forthwith reads everything in the eyes of lovers. The man who is honest and
good ought to be exactly like a man who smells strong, so that the bystander as soon
as he comes near him must smell whether he chews or not. Nothing is more disgraceful than
a wolfish friendship, false friendship. Avoid this most of all. See? Bossed! As to living
in the best way, this power is in the soul, if it be indifferent to things which are
indifferent. You need to add some text for me to talk, and it will be indifferent.
If it looks on each of these things separately and altogether, and if it remembers that not
one of them produces in us an opinion about itself, nor comes to us, but these things
remain immovable, power not to write them, and it being in our power, if perchance
these judgments have imperceptibly got admission to our minds, to wipe them out,
and if we remember also that such attention will only be for a short time,
and then life will be at an end. Besides, what trouble is there at all in doing this?
For if these things are according to nature, rejoice in them, and they will be easy to
thee. But if contrary to nature, seek what is conformable to thy own nature,
and strive towards this even if it bring no reputation, for every man is allowed to
seek his own good, consider whence each thing is come, and of what it consists,
and into what it changes, and what kind of a thing it will be when it is changed,
and that it will sustain no harm. Any have offended against thee. Consider first,
what is my relation to men, and that we are made for one another,
and in another respect I was made to be set over them as a ram over the flock,
or a bull over the herd. But examine the matter from first principles. From this,
if all things are not mere atoms, it is nature which orders all things. If this is so,
the inferior things exist for the sake of the superior, and these for the sake of one
another. Second, consider what kind of men they are at table, in bed, and so forth,
and particularly, under what compulsions in respect of opinions they are, are and as to
their acts. Consider with what pride they do what they do. Third, that if men do rightly
what they do, we ought not to be displeased, but if they do not right, it is plain that
they do so involuntarily and in ignorance. For as every soul is unwillingly deprived
of the truth, so also is it unwillingly deprived of the power of behaving to each man
according to his deserts. Accordingly, men are pained when they are called unjust,
ungrateful, and greedy, and in a word, wrongdoers to their neighbours. Fourth,
consider that thou also doest many things wrong, and that thou art a man like others,
and even if thou dost abstain from certain faults, still thou hast the disposition to
commit them, though either through cowardice or concern about reputation or some such mean
motive thou dost abstain from such faults. Fifth, consider that thou dost not even
understand whether men are doing wrong or not, for many things are done with a certain
reference to circumstances. And sixth, consider when thou art much vexed or grieved,
that man's life is only a moment, and after a short time we are all laid out dead.
Seventh, that it is not men's acts which disturb us, for those acts have their
foundation in men's ruling principles, but it is our own opinions which disturb us.
Take away these opinions, then, and resolve to dismiss thy judgment about an act as if
it were something grievous, and thy anger is gone, by reflecting that no wrongful act
of another brings shame on thee, for unless that which is shameful is alone bad, thou
also must of necessity do many things wrong. Eighth, consider how much more pain is brought
on us by the anger and vexation caused by such acts than by the acts themselves,
at which we are angry and vexed. For what will the most violent man do to thee,
if thou continuest to be of a kind disposition towards him? And if, as opportunity offers,
thou gently admonishest him, and calmly correctest his errors at the very time
when he is trying to do thee harm, saying, Not so, my child. We are constituted by nature
for something else. Be injured, but thou art injuring thyself, my child, and show him
with gentle tact, and by general principles, that this is so, and that even bees do not do
as he does, nor any animals which are formed by nature to be gregarious. And thou must do
this neither with any double meaning nor in the way of reproach, but affectionately and
without any rancour in thy soul, and not as if thou wert lecturing. Him, nor yet that
any bystander may admire, but either when he is alone, and if others are in present.
Remember these nine rules, as if thou hadst received them as a gift from the muses,
and begin at last to be a man while thou livest. But thou must equally avoid flattering men and
being vexed at them, for both are unsocial and lead to harm. You need to add some text for me
to talk. And let this truth be present to thee in the excitement of anger, that to be
moved by passion is not manly, but that mildness and gentleness, as they are more agreeable to
human nature, so also are they more manly. And he who possesses these qualities possesses
strength, nerves, and courage. For in the same degree in which a man's mind is nearer
to freedom from all passion, in the same degree also is it nearer to strength. And
a sense of pain is a characteristic of weakness, so also is anger. For he who yields to pain,
and he who yields to anger, both are wounded, and both submit. But if thou wilt, receive also
a tenth present from the leader of the muses, Apollo. And it is this that to expect bad men
not to do wrong is madness, for he who expects this desires an impossibility. You
aberrations of the superior faculty, against which thou shouldst be constantly on thy guard.
And when thou hast detected them, thou shouldst wipe them out, and say on each occasion thus,
This thought is not necessary. This tends to destroy social union. This which thou art
going to say comes not from the real thoughts. For thou shouldst consider it among the most
absurd of things, for a man not to speak from his real thoughts, but to allow men to behave so
to others, and to expect them not to do thee any wrong, is irrational and tyrannical.
But the fourth is when thou shalt reproach thyself for anything. For this is an evidence
of the diviner part, within thee and being overpowered, and yielding to the less
and to the perishable part, the body, and to its gross, thy areo part.
And all the fiery parts which are mingled in thee, though by nature they have an upward
tendency, still in obedience to the disposition of the universe, they are overpowered here in
the compound mass, the body, and also the whole of the earthy part in thee, and the watery,
though their tendency is downward, still are raised up and occupy a position which is not
their natural one. In this manner, then, the elemental parts obey the universal, for when
they have been fixed in any place per force, they remain there until, again, the universal
shall sound the signal. Is it not then strange that thy intelligent part only should be
disobedient and discontented with its own place, and yet no force is imposed on it,
but only those things which are conformable to its nature? Still it does not submit,
but is carried in the opposite direction. For the movement towards injustice and intemperance
and to anger and grief and fear is nothing else than the act of one who deviates from
nature. And also, when the ruling faculty is discontented with anything that happens,
then too it deserts its post, for it is constituted for piety and reverence towards
the gods, no less than for justice. For these qualities also are comprehended under the
generic term of contentment with the constitution of things, and indeed they are prior to acts
of justice. But what I have said is not enough, unless this also is added, what this object
ought to be. For as there is not the same opinion about all the things, which in some
way or other are considered by the majority to be good, but only about some certain things,
that is, things which concern the common interest, ourselves an object which shall
be of a common kind, social and political. For he who directs all his own efforts to this object
will make all his acts alike, and thus will always be the same. Socrates used to call
the opinions of the many, by the name of Lamiae, bug-bears to frighten children.
The Lacedaemonians at their public spectacles used to set seats in the shade for strangers,
but themselves sat down anywhere. Socrates excused himself to Perdiccas for not going to
him, saying, It is because I would not perish by the worst of all ends. That is, I would
not receive a favor and then be unable to return it. In the writings of the Ephesians
there was this precept constantly to think of some one of the men of former times who
practiced virtue. The Pythagoreans bid us in the morning look to the heavens, that we may be
reminded of those bodies which continually do the same things and in the same manner perform
their work, and also be reminded of their purity and nudity. For there is no veil over
a star. Neither in writing nor in reading wilt thou be able to lay down rules for others
before thou shalt have first learned to obey rules thyself. Much more is nisso in life.
And my heart laughed within. When a man kisses his child, said Epictetus, he should whisper to
himself, To morrow perchance thou wilt die. But those are words of bad omen.
You need to add some text for me to talk. Epictetus also said, A man must discover
an art, or rules, with respect to giving his assent, and in respect to his movements he
must be careful that they be made with regard to circumstances, that they be consistent with
social interests, that they have regard to the value of the object. From it,
and as to avoidance, aversion, he should not show it with respect to any of the
things which are not in our power. The unripe grape, the ripe bunch, the dried grape,
all are changes, not into nothing, but into something which exists not yet.
No man can rob us of our free will. The dispute then, he said, is not about any common
matter, but about being mad or not. And Socrates used to say, What do you want?
Souls of rational men, or irrational? Souls of rational men, of what rational men?
Sound or unsound? Sound. Why then do you not seek for them? Because we have them.
Why then do you fight and quarrel? Book 12
All those things at which thou wishest to arrive by a circuitous road,
thou canst have now, if thou dost not refuse them to thyself.
And this means, if thou wilt take no notice of all the past, and trust the future to providence,
and direct the present only conformably to piety and justice, conformably to piety,
that thou mayest be content with the lot which is assigned to thee, for nature designed it for
thee and thee for it, conformably to justice, that thou mayest always speak the truth freely
and without disguise, and do the things which are agreeable to law, and according to the worth of
each. If then, whatever the time may be, when thou shalt be near to thy departure,
neglecting everything else, thou shalt respect only thy ruling faculty and the divinity within
thee. And if thou shalt be afraid, worthy of the universe which has produced thee,
and thou wilt cease to be a stranger in thy native land, and to wonder at things which
happened daily, as if they were something unexpected, and to be dependent on this or that,
and let neither another man's wickedness hinder thee, nor opinion nor voice, nor yet the
sensations of the poor flesh which has grown about thee, for the passive part will look to
this. For with his intellectual part alone, he touches the intelligence only which has flowed,
men being derived from himself into these bodies. And if thou also usest thyself to do this,
thou wilt rid thyself of thy much trouble. For he who regards not the poor flesh which
envelops him, surely will not trouble himself by looking after raiment and dwelling and fame
and suchlike externals, and show. You need to add some text for me to talk. Therefore,
if thou shalt separate from thyself, that is, from thy understanding,
whatever others do or say, and whatever thou hast done or said thyself,
and whatever future things troubled thee because they may happen,
and whatever in the body which envelops thee, or in the breath, life which is by nature
associated with the body, the independent of thy will, and whatever the external
vortex whirls round, so that the intellectual power exempt from the things of fate can live
pure and free by itself, doing what is just, and accepting what happens, and saying the truth,
if thou wilt separate, I say. You need to add some text for me to talk.
The impressions of sense, and the things of time to come, and of time that is past,
and wilt make thyself, like Empedocles's sphere, all round and in its joyous rest reposing.
Of thy death, free from perturbations, nobly and obedient to thy own daemon,
to the God that is within thee, of these the first two are thine,
so far as it is thy duty to take care of them. But the third alone is properly thine.
If, then, a God or a wise teacher should present himself to a man, and bid him to think of nothing,
and to design nothing which he would not express as soon as he conceived it,
he could not endure it even for a single day. You need to add some text for me to talk.
How can it be that the gods, after having arranged all things well and benevolently for
mankind, have overlooked this alone, that some men, and very good men,
should never exist again but should be completely extinguished?
So much more respect have we to what our neighbors shall think of us
than to what we shall think of ourselves. But if this is so, be assured that if it ought
to have been otherwise, the gods would have done it. You need to add some text for me to talk.
But because it is not so, if in fact it is not so, be thou convinced that it ought not to have
been so. For thou seest even of thyself, that in this inquiry thou art disputing with the
deity, ordering of the universe to be neglected unjustly and irrationally. For if it were just,
it would also be possible, and if it were according to nature, nature would have had it
so. Practice thyself even in the things which thou despairest of accomplishing.
For even the left hand, which is ineffectual for all other things, for want of practice,
holds the bridle more vigorously than the right hand. For it has been. Consider in what
condition both in body and soul a man should be when he is overtaken by death, and n consider
the shortness of life, the boundless abyss of time, past and future, the feebleness of all
matter. Contemplate the formative principles, forms, of things bare of their coverings,
the purposes of actions. Consider what pain is, what pleasure is. In the application of thy
principles, thou must be like the pancratiast, not like the gladiator. For the gladiator lets
fall, the sword which he uses and is killed, but the other always has his hand, and needs
to do nothing else than use it. See what things are in themselves, dividing them into matter,
form, and purpose. What a power man has to do nothing except what God will approve,
and to accept all that God may give him. With respect to that which happens conformably
we ought to blame neither gods, for they do nothing wrong either voluntarily or involuntarily
nor men. Consequently we should blame nobody. How ridiculous and what a stranger he is who
is surprised at anything which happens in life. Either there is a fatal necessity,
an invincible order, or a kind providence, or a confusion without a purpose and without
a director. If, then, there is an invincible necessity, why dost thou resist? But if there
is a providence which allows itself to be propitiated, make thyself worthy of the
help of the divinity. But, if there is a confusion without in governor, be content
that in such a tempest thou hast in thyself a certain ruling intelligence. And even if
carry thee away, let it carry away the poor flesh, the poor breath, everything else,
for the intelligence, at least it will not carry away. Does the light of the lamp
shine without losing its splendour until it is extinguished, and shall the truth
which is in thee and justice and temperance be extinguished before thy death? What a man
has presented the appearance of having done wrong, say, How, then, do I know if this
is a wrongful act? Consider that he who would not have the bad man do wrong is like
the man who would not have the fig-tree to bear juice in the figs and infants to
cry and the horse to neigh, and whatever else must of necessity be. For what must
a man do who has such a character? If, then, thou art irritable, cure this man's
disposition. If it is not right, do not do it. If it is not true, do not say it.
For let thy efforts be, in everything always observe what the thing is which produces
for thee an appearance, and resolve it by dividing it into the formal, the material,
the. Perceive at last that thou hast in thee something better, and more divine than
the things which cause the various effects. And as it were, pull thee by the strings.
What is there now in my mind? Is it fear, or suspicion, or desire, or anything of
the kind? First, do nothing inconsiderately, nor without a purpose. Second, make thy acts
refer to nothing else than to a social end. E.N. Consider that, E.N. Consider that,
before long thou wilt be nobody. For all things are formed by nature to change
and to be turned, and to perish, in order that other things in continuous succession
may exist. Consider that everything is opinion, and opinion is in thy power.
Take away, then, when thou choosest thy opinion, and like a mariner,
who has doubled the promontory, thou wilt find calm, everything stable,
and a waveless bay. Any one activity, whatever it may be, when it has ceased at
its proper time, suffers no evil. Because it has ceased, nor he who has done this act,
does he suffer any evil for this reason. In like manner, then, the whole which consists
of all the acts, which is our life, if it cease at its proper time, suffers no evil
for this reason that it has ceased. Nor he who has terminated this series at the proper time
has he been ill dealt with. But the proper time and the limit nature fixes, sometimes,
as in old age, the peculiar nature of man, but always the universal nature, by the change
of whose parts the whole universe continues, ever young and perfect. And everything which
is useful to the universal is always good, and in season. Therefore the termination of
for every man is no evil, because neither is it shameful, since it is both independent of the
will, and not opposed to the general interest, but it is good, since it is seasonable and
profitable to, and congruent with, the universal. For thus, too, he is moved by the
Deity, who is moved in the same manner with the Deity, and moved towards the same things
in his mind. In the things which thou doest, do nothing, either ninconsiderately or otherwise,
than as justice herself would act, but with respect to what may happen to thee from, without,
consider that it happens either by chance or according to providence, and thou must
neither blame chance nor accuse providence. Second, consider what every being is, from the
seed to the time of its receiving a soul, and from the reception of a soul to the giving
back of the same, and of what things every being is compounded, and into what things it
is resolved. You need to add some text for me to talk. Third, if thou shouldst suddenly be raised
up above the earth, and shouldst look down on human things, and observe the variety of them,
how great it is, and at the same time also shouldst see, at a glance, how great is the
number of beings who dwell around in the air and the ether, consider that, as often as
be raised up, thou wouldst see the same things, sameness of form and shortness of duration.
When thou art troubled about anything, thou hast forgotten this, that all things happen
according to the universal nature, and forgotten this, that a man's wrongful act is nothing to
thee. How close is the kinship between a man and the whole human race, for it is a community,
not of a little blood or seed, but of intelligence. You need to add some text for me to talk,
and thou hast forgotten this, too, that every man's intelligence is a god, and is an efflux
of the deity, and forgotten this, that nothing is a man's own, but that his child and his body
and his very soul came from the deity, forgotten this, that everything is opinion,
and lastly, thou hast forgotten that every man lives the present time only, and loses only
this. In constantly bring to thy recollection those who have complained greatly about
anything, those who have been most conspicuous by the greatest fame or misfortunes or enmities
or fortunes of any kind, violently strain, and how much more philosophical it is for a
man and the opportunities presented to him to show, are these things to be proud of?